<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The king of terrors silenced by meditations &amp; examples of holy living and heavenly dying as the same was recollected and recommended by Sir John Thorowgood.</title>
            <author>Thorowgood, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25161</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08781250</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08781250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41807</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62470)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41807)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1270:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The king of terrors silenced by meditations &amp; examples of holy living and heavenly dying as the same was recollected and recommended by Sir John Thorowgood.</title>
                  <author>Thorowgood, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To be distributed among his kindred and his friends at his funeral."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations.</term>
               <term>Devotional exercises.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE King of Terrors SILENCED, BY Meditations &amp; Examples OF HOLY LIVING AND HEAVENLY DYING, As the ſame was Recollected and Recommended By Sir <hi>John Thorowgood</hi> of <hi>Kenſington,</hi> Knight, To be diſtributed among his Kindred and his Friends at his Funeral.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Contra vim mortis,</l>
               <l>Non eſt medicamen in hortis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:4"/>
            <head>To ſuch Friends as ſhall be invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to accompany my <hi>CORPSE</hi> to the Earth.</head>
            <p>THere be many uſeful <hi>Treatiſes</hi> ſet forth upon this <hi>ſubject</hi> (the Lord be bleſſed) concerning <hi>Mans mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and for the Preparation and the Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of all ſuch as do minde their <hi>frail condition,</hi> and their ſouls <hi>ſalvation.</hi> This, that I do here <hi>offer</hi> to you, as it hath been for many years in my <hi>thoughts,</hi> and for the moſt part <hi>prepared:</hi> ſo now, upon daily expectation of leaving this <hi>evil world,</hi> do I intend it only for the uſe of ſome <hi>particular Friends;</hi> who, I preſume, will prize it before the beſt <hi>Marchpane,</hi> and prefer it before thoſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent entertainments, by <hi>Gloves,</hi> or <hi>Rings,</hi> or <hi>Ribbons.</hi> In our <hi>Health</hi> we have profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Sermons,</hi> and godly <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Company,</hi> and holy mens <hi>Books,</hi> to repair unto for <hi>ſoul-refreſhment;</hi> but, in a retired <hi>languiſhing,</hi> painful <hi>ſickneſs,</hi> we may perhaps, be deprived of moſt of theſe:
<pb facs="tcp:41807:5"/> For this cauſe I have here gathered, into as ſmall a <hi>Volume</hi> as may be, much of it, from other mens <hi>heavenly Meditations,</hi> that, which takes in the four ſeveral ſeaſons of <hi>decaying man;</hi> relating, <hi>1.</hi> To the time of his <hi>preſent health. 2.</hi> To his <hi>firſt ſickning. 3.</hi> To the <hi>keeping his Chamber. 4.</hi> To certain ſignes of <hi>approaching Death. 5.</hi> To theſe is added, (for the welcoming of it) ſome remarkable Examples of holy mens <hi>cheerful deportment</hi> in their Chriſtianly departing out of this <hi>mortal Life.</hi> To hold you too long in an <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> is not proper for ſuch an occaſion as <hi>this;</hi> and therefore I ſhall draw to a <hi>concluſion,</hi> and only recommend <hi>it,</hi> and all you my good <hi>Friends,</hi> to the great Lord and Maſter of us all, the Lord Jeſus Christ; who is the <hi>Propitiation for our ſins,</hi> and by whom we are <hi>reconciled to the Father:</hi> in <hi>humble aſſurance</hi> whereof, I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſupported Friend, JOHN THOROWGOOD.</signed>
               <dateline>Kenſington
<date>
                     <hi>May 1. 1664.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:5"/>
            <head>A Friendly CAUTION.</head>
            <l>TO you my Friends, that I ſhall leave behinde,</l>
            <l>Do I bequeath this Gift, where you may finde</l>
            <l>Some helps to uſe, when you moſt helpleſs are;</l>
            <l>So to make it, hath been my earneſt care:</l>
            <l>Peruſe it then in Health, that ſo ye may</l>
            <l>Be ready and preparing every day,</l>
            <l>To welcome him, that's call'd the King of Fears,</l>
            <l>That with him endleſs pain or comfort bears.</l>
            <l>Then take it in good part, and read and pray,</l>
            <l>That it may profit till your dying day:</l>
            <l>Take heed betimes of cuſtomary ſin,</l>
            <l>If ever ye intend Heavens joys to win.</l>
            <l>Let not your boſome-ſin have any reſt;</l>
            <l>Let it not lodge one night within your breſt:</l>
            <l>Take heed, I ſay, no evil do prevail,</l>
            <l>If't do, be ſure that it you do bewail</l>
            <l>With ſighs and tears, with ſorrow and with care,</l>
            <l>Of thoughts, and words, and actions to beware.</l>
            <l>Here pray again, with faith and godly fear,</l>
            <l>That God your ſuit moſt graciouſly will hear;</l>
            <l>That you may conquer ſelf, and live and die,</l>
            <l>And fix the ſafety of your ſoul on high.</l>
            <l>Thus do I pray, thus will I pray, ſo long,</l>
            <l>So long as I have breath, or life, or tongue.</l>
            <l>Now farewel Friends; good Lord, I come to thee,</l>
            <l>Who ever wert a Saviour unto me:</l>
            <l>Receive me to thy ſelf, and let me bring</l>
            <l>A ſoul full ſer, <hi>Halleluja</hi>'s to ſing,</l>
            <l>(In that bleſt Quire, and with that heavenly Hoſt)</l>
            <l>Glory to Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your revived Friend, <hi>J. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:6"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>PART. I. Meditations in time of Health.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> SHort Sentences to minde us of our Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>Page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> A Prayer in Health, preparing for Death <hi>Page 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Meditations of Gods mercies <hi>Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Of the danger and evil of Sin <hi>Page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Health, the fitteſt time for Repentance <hi>Page 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Holy reſolutions in time of Health <hi>Page 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Meditations concerning Sickneſs <hi>Page 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Remedies againſt Sin <hi>Page 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Meditations of Death <hi>Page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Reſolutions againſt the vexations and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the World. <hi>Page 25</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PART II. Meditations at firſt Sickning.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. A</hi> Prayer in time of Sickneſs <hi>Page 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Concerning Prayer <hi>Page 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Meditations at firſt ſickning <hi>Page 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Directions and conſolations in time of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Death <hi>Page 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> A Prayer before taking of Phyſick <hi>Page 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> A Prayer before Phyſick is working <hi>Page 44</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41807:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Six Meditations to cure the fear of Death <hi>Page 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Rules to make our Calling and Election ſure <hi>Page 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Againſt doubtings of Gods mercy <hi>Page 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Reading of Chapters, or portions of Scripture <hi>Page 55</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PART III. Meditations at growing Weak.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. A</hi> Prayer upon danger of Death <hi>Page 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Conſolations concerning death <hi>Page 60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Againſt impatience in Sickneſs <hi>Page 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Conſolations in the Lord Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c. Page 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Reading of Scripture, or part of Chap. <hi>Page 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> A Prayer where friends are to joyn <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Meditations upon the dayes of Death and of Doom <hi>Page 72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Short Prayers upon any releaſe of pain <hi>Page 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Conſolations againſt pain and fear of dying <hi>Page 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Ejaculations to Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt <hi>Page 79</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PART IV. Meditations upon certain ſignes of Death.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> SHort Prayers upon any intermiſſion of Pain <hi>Page 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> A Prayer to be uſed by Friends <hi>Page 82</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41807:7"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Queſtions with Anſwers, upon any ſigne of Dying <hi>Page 85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Portions of Scripture to be read <hi>Page 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> More Queſtions and Anſwers <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Short Prayers upon any abating of pain <hi>Page 90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Friends to help with ſhort Ejaculations <hi>Page 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> More of theſe ſhort Ejaculations <hi>Page 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> A Prayer by Friends at leaving this Life <hi>Page 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Another by Friends, at yielding up the Ghoſt <hi>Page 95</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PART V. Being ten bleſſed Examples of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſons, relating to a happy paſſage out of this Life to a better.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> THe Sickneſs and Death of the Earle of <hi>Hanaw Page 97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The laſt words of Mr. <hi>John Meautys Page 113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Juxons</hi> Life and Death <hi>Page 114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh's</hi> Life and Death <hi>Page 118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Mr. <hi>Rhodes</hi> his Life and Death <hi>Page 123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Rhodes</hi> her Life and Death <hi>Page 128</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Dr. <hi>Harris</hi> his Life and Death <hi>Page 133</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Scot</hi>'s Life and Death <hi>Page 141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX. Monſieur du Moulins</hi> Life and Death <hi>Page 149</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Mr. <hi>Crook</hi>'s Life and Death <hi>Page 156</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41807:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>PART I. Meditations in time of Health.</head>
            <div n="1" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Short ſentences to minde us of our Mortality.</head>
               <p>NUllum momentum, ſine motu ad mortem.</p>
               <p>Quotidie morimur, quotidie enim demitur pars vitae, &amp; tunc quoque cum creſcimus, vita decreſcit.</p>
               <p>Mille modis morimur mortales, naſcimur uno.</p>
               <p>Sunt hominum morbi mille, ſed una ſalus.</p>
               <p>Non eſt malum in morte, niſi poſt mortem.</p>
               <p>Oſſa arida &amp; ſepulchra, ſunt praeceprores noſtri.</p>
               <p>Qui moritur vitiis antequam moritur corpore, non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur morte aeterna, quando moritur morte corporis.</p>
               <p>Summum hominis bonum, bonus ex hac vita exitus.</p>
               <p>Naſci &amp; mori, commune eſt Regi &amp; populo, diviti &amp; paupero, fortunato &amp; miſero.</p>
               <p>Fleres ſi ſcires unum tua tempora menſem,</p>
               <p>Rides quum non ſit forſitan una dies.</p>
               <p>Ante ſenectutem curavi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bene viverem; in ſene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctute, ut bene moriar.</p>
               <p>In mundo, ſpes nulla boni, ſpes nulla ſalutis.</p>
               <p>Una ſalus ſervire Deo, ſunt caetera fraudes.</p>
               <p>Pulvis &amp; umbra ſumus, pulvis nihil eſt niſi fumus:</p>
               <p>Sed nihil eſt fumus, nos nihil ergo ſumus.</p>
               <p>Dic homo, quid ſperes, qui mundo totus adhaeres?</p>
               <p>Tecum nulla feres, licet omnia ſolus haberes.</p>
               <p>Heu fugiunt fraeno, non remorante, dies.</p>
               <p>Mors tua, mors Chriſti, fraus mundi, gloria coeli,</p>
               <p>Et dolor inferni, ſint meditanda tibi.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subpart">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41807:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> A Prayer in health preparing for death. <hi>Qui orat &amp; peccat, non orat ſed deludit.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt gracious Lord, the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh; thou which haſt the keyes of death and of Hell; thou which haſt prepared and ruleſt them both at thy good pleaſure: I humbly beſeech thee be merciful to thy poor creature, and preſerve me from the terrors which are ready to ſeize upon me. O Lord, when I do ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how I dwell in a houſe of clay, the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being in the duſt, and how I muſt ere long make my bed in the dark, my ſpirit doth ſeem to fail, and my heart to faint; eſpecially being told out of thy bleſſed Word, That <hi>the ſting of death is ſin,</hi> and ſo mine own ſin. O raiſe me up from ſad and unquiet thoughts: teach me how to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all diſcouragements; and help me to call to minde thoſe truths, As that the nature of death is to thy ſervants quite altered; that the ſting is plucked out, and it ſelf ſwallowed up in victory: O help me to conſider, how by death thy poor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſhall be freed from ſickneſs of body, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of minde; from ſinning againſt thy heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Majeſty, and from the ſociety of the wicked. Teach me truly to confeſs, and humbly to bewail my manifold offences, and then effectually to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thy gracious promiſes to my everlaſting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41807:8"/> that ſo all fainting fears proceeding from the ſence of my ſins, may turn to holy rejoycing, with a cheerful expecting, and even to an earneſt longing for the time of my diſſolution. And yet, that I may not beguile mine own ſoul, in laying claim to that ſpiritual refreſhing which belongs not to me; make me to labour diligently for thoſe aſſured evidences, and undeceiving fore-runners of a happy departure. I have been taught, O Lord, that if I live here without conſcience, I ſhall aſſuredly die without comfort; that holineſs here, is the ſafe and certain way to happineſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; that I muſt ſeek to glorifie thee, if I mean to be glorified with thee; that I muſt fight the good fight of faith, both againſt Satan, againſt the world, and againſt mine own corruptions; that I muſt faithfully finiſh my courſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably perform the ſervice to which thou haſt appointed me; that I muſt know thy Law, and keep the faith in ſoundneſs and ſincerity to the end, otherwiſe it will be in vain to expect a crown of righteouſneſs; that I muſt come to the firſt reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection that is from ſin, or elſe I ſhall never eſcape the ſecond death: O Lord, grant me therefore of thy heavenly grace, that henceforth I may more carefully ſerve thee in holineſs and righteouſneſs all the dayes of my life; endeavouring alwayes, and in all things, to have and to keep a clear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards thee, and towards all men. Lord,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41807:9"/> kill my corruptions in me, that I may be even dead to ſin, but alive to thee in Jeſus Chriſt: affect my ſoul with a ſence and an aſſurance of thoſe heavenly joyes, which may work in my heart both fear and love alſo to thee the God of all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And becauſe, if I live after the fleſh (ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king though for it) to fulfil it, I ſhall die; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech thee to mortifie in me the deeds of the body by thy Spirit, that ſo I may have my fruit in holineſs, and that my end may be everlaſting life. Teach me, and enable me to be alwayes num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring my dayes, and to conſider the uncertain cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of my latter end, that I may be dying eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, ſtill looking, and ſtill preparing for my change, and making account that each day (by one means or other) may be the day of my diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Strengthen alſo, good Lord, my weak and fainting faith; make me ſtrong in thee, and in the power of thy might: ſeal me with the holy ſpirit of promiſe, as with the earneſt of my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly inheritance, that ſo no tribulation in this world may diſquiet me, no anguiſh in ſickneſs diſcourage me, no aſſault of Satan over come me; but that, come life, ſo long as thou pleaſeſt, or come death, when or how it ſhall ſeem good unto thee, I may cheerfully, and through Chriſt, commit my ſoul to thee, as to a faithful Creator. Grant me, O Lord, theſe fatherly bleſſings, and what elſe thou in thine infinite wiſdom knoweſt better what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41807:9"/> is needful for me; and that for his ſake, who died to free me from death, even Jeſus Chriſt the righteous; to whom with thee and the holy Spirit, be given all honour, praiſe and glory, now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Meditations of Gods mercies.</head>
               <p>AMong all the infinite treaſures, wherewith the largeneſs of the Godhead aboundeth, there is nothing that refreſheth, relieveth us miſerable ſinners, worms of the earth, that lye low at his footſtool, but the conſideration of Gods mercy. His Majeſty aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, his glory beateth us down, his greatneſs ſtriketh us dead; we adore his omnipotence, admire his wiſdom, ſtand in aw of his juſtice, flie from his vengeance: In mercy, in mercy alone it is, that we taſte how gracious, and how amiable the Lord is; of all Gods attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, none is more eminent then his mercy. Bleſſed be her womb that bare us, and her paps that gave us ſuck: we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41807:10"/> live, and move, and have our being by her; ſhe grew up with us from our youth, and forſaketh us not when we be grey-headed; ſhe giveth us our daily bread, and hourly breath; ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth us in life, comforteth us in death, and crowneth us with ſalvation. O mercy, the Lady and Empreſs of all the attributes of God! what ſhall we ſay of thee? Heaven and earth are full of thy glory: The glorious company of the Prophets praiſe thee; the goodly fellowſhip of the Apoſtles praiſe thee; the noble army of the Martyrs praiſe thee; the holy Church throughout the world doth knowledge thee. Thy mercy, O Lord, doth ſhine upon us every way. There is, 1. Thy preventing mercy; from whence I may ſay, that unleſs the Lord had preſerved me by his grace and power, my ſoul had launched out into the fouleſt ſins. 2. There is thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing mercy, whereby thou doſt wait for the converſion of foul offenders. 3. There is thy altering mercy, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41807:10"/> from vanity and vice, doth ſettle us in wayes of holineſs. 4. There is thy imbracing mercy, whereby thou aſſureſt us (being now converted) of thy favour in Chriſt Jeſus. 5. There is thy confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy, which ſtrengthens us in the courſe of godlineſs. 6. There is thy comforting mercy, which ſets us in the hope and expectation of future glory. 7. There is thy crowning mercy, which gives us aſſurance and full poſſeſſion of eternal happineſs in the Kingdom of Heaven. Yea Lord, thy boundleſs mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies do every where, and every way, and every day, moſt graciouſly inlarge themſelves towards us, both in giving us all good things, and in forgiving us all our offendings: but yet it muſt be our care, that we take heed never to preſume upon this mercy, but to have this ſentence alwayes in our mindes and memories, <hi>The Lord is merciful, that he may be feared.</hi> Amen. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subpart">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41807:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Of the danger and evil of Sin.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHo would be ſo hardy as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any one ſin, if he did at all conſider the examples of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for ſin! and that firſt, Upon the whole world which he had made: 2. Upon his Church, the quinteſſence of the world, when they ſinned in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs. 3. Upon his Saints, the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of his Church; as <hi>David,</hi> his beloved. 4. On the Angels in Heaven offending. 5. On his dear Son himſelf, when he took our ſins upon him, and ſo felt the bitterneſs of Gods juſtice: upon which one ſayes well; <hi>Magna ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> amaritudo peccati, quae tantam amaritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem peperit; Great was the ſowrneſs in our ſinning, that produced ſo great ſharpneſs in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuffering.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Alas, what avails it for an impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinner to ſeek for outward relief, when our Executioner is within us! If we could ſhift from our ſelves, we might
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41807:11"/> have ſome hope of eaſe: but what if we could run from our ſelves? Alas, that's nothing! Our ſouls may flie from our bodies; but our conſcience will not flie from our ſouls, nor our ſins from our conſcience. Some indeed, in the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theſe pangs of ſins, have leapt out of this private hell, that is in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, into that common pit of hell; chuſing rather to adventure on the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture pains that they have feared, then to endure the preſent horrors that they have felt; gaining hereby nothing, but to that hell which was within them, a ſecond hell to be without them. The conſcience leaves not where the fiends begin; but both together joyn in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What can we think of ſin? let the pleaſure, or the profit, or the pretence thereof be what it may be; yet before the execution of the leaſt ſin, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, That either we muſt repent that ſin, and that with a ſorrow equal to the pleaſure that we had in it, or elſe we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41807:12"/> ſhall for that one ſin be condemned to everlaſting torments. Let this then, O let this only one conſideration ſink deep, and dwell upon our hearts, and then it will prove a help to us during our life.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Some obdurate foreheads there be, that would ſeem to laugh their ſins out of countenance; but certainly their hearts muſt needs bleed, when their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do countenance a ſmile; they do wear out many waking hours, when they think they reſt: yea, as their thoughts afford them no ſleep, no more does their ſleep afford them reſt; but while their ſences are tyed up, their ſin is let looſe, frighting them with horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dreams: <hi>Therefore ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. See, the tongue of a ſinner begins firſt to diſſemble, next to lye, next to ſwear, next to blaſpheme; and the next thing that the ſinner takes in hand, is the practiſe of evil actions: And here (as in other caſes) the devil uſeth his old method; he firſt teaches the man the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41807:12"/> art of fraud and coſening; after that, the practiſe of extortion and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; then the trade of open theft and violence: ſo as, by this time the man is grown a perfect artiſt and proficient, being ſhewn the way to ſwallow any bait, and to ſcruple at nothing at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Health, the fitteſt time for Repentance.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LEt us not delay our Repentance from day to day, but even in our youth begin ſo neceſſary, ſo profitable a work. Can we think it fit to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take (by the ſerious exerciſes of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which is the work of works) to turn our ſinful ſouls towards God, when ſickneſs has ſeized upon us, and when we are not able to turn our tyred limbs upon our ſofteſt bed? If we finde it ſo hard a matter to turn to heavenward now, we ſhall finde it far harder then: for our ſin will wax ſtronger every day, but our ſtrength for reſiſtance will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come weaker; our conſcience will frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us, pain will diſtract us, fear of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41807:13"/> death will amaze us, viſiting of friends will diſturb us; ſo as if we be not before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand furniſhed with a competency of faith, and patience, and holy conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we ſhall not on our ſick beds, be able to meditate our ſelves, nor to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the words of counſel or of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from others; we ſhall not be able to pray alone, nor to joyn with others that would pray with us: therefore let us beware, and begin Repentance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. He ſhall be ſure to forget God at his death, that did not daily remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him in his life: let us then prepare our ſelves betimes for ſickneſs and death; let us pull out the ſting of death, by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bewailing of ſins paſt, by timely cleaving to God for the future, with purpoſing and practiſing ſincerity of life and converſation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God; our ſins are the <hi>Egyptians</hi> that keep us in bondage: let us pray, that theſe <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> may be drowned in that red Sea, and waſhed away by that precious blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41807:13"/>3. In our health let us take heed of all ſins; for ſins are the only enemies to Chriſt: they be thoſe ſouldiers that apprehended him; thoſe tormentors that ſcourged him; thoſe thorns that gored his head; thoſe nails that pierced his feet; that ſpear that ſpilt his blood; that Croſs that took away his life.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Take heed; for he that doth not repent to day, hath a day more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of, and yet a day leſs to repent in. It was the ſaying of a holy man, when he heard a clock to ſtrike: <hi>Hark, here is one hour more that I have to anſwer for.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Defer not repentance till ſickneſs come; it may preſently be violent; and then, if our reaſon continue (which is oftentimes otherwiſe) it will be moſt neceſſary to imploy that reaſon and our beſt thoughts on the higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, on the world that we are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, and not on the world that we are about to leave: let terrene things always give place to celeſtial things, that ſo we may be in Heaven here.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subpart">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41807:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Holy reſolutions in time of Health.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Will alwayes remember, That the greateſt task that I have to finiſh in this world, it is to die well, and to make a happy departure out of this life: for they which die well, die not to die, but to live for ever.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When I would do any good, or receive any good, I will offer up mine endeavours in a ſacrifice to thee, O Lord, in Chriſt; beſeeching thee to give thine holy Spirit to ſanctifie this thine own ſacrifice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In all mine actions I will ſeek to redeem the time of my life that is paſt, with ſad and ſerious repentance: I will regard and conſider the time preſent with care and diligence; and be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the time to come with provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Among other my daily buſineſs, I wil be ſure to exerciſe my ſelf in reading of ſomething out of the Word of God;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41807:14"/> and alſo to be careful, not only to ſerve God my ſelf, but to ſee that all under my charge ſhall do the ſame.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I will account of every day, as of the day of my death; and will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to live now, as though I were even now to die: I will do thoſe duties every day, which I would be doing if it were my laſt day.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whatſoever I ſhall undertake in this life, I will enjoy that and all things in God, and ſo God in all things, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it ſelf; ſo ſhall my joyes neither change nor periſh: for howſoever the things themſelves may alter or fade, yet he, in whom they are mine, is not alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but ever like himſelf, faithful, permanent and everlaſting.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Paſſions are ſaid to be either ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcible, as ſorrow, hatred, anger; or elſe concupiſcible, as love, deſire, joy, hope: In both of them I will be careful to uſe a great deal of moderation: I may love the creature, but I will not adore it; I will not love the creature more then the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41807:15"/> Creator: I may deſire, but not all things equally; not earth in compariſon of Heaven: I may rejoyce, but that joy ſhall be ſober and ſpiritual: I may hope, but not for impoſſibilities: I may be angry, but not to ſin: I may weep, but chiefly for ſin.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In pleaſures and recreations, I will not be ſo much given up to <hi>jocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> as to forget <hi>utile &amp; honeſtum:</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures may blaze for a while like crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thorns, but they preſently vaniſh, and quickly come to nothing. O Lord, let theſe reſolutions turn to prayers; and let thoſe prayers obtain a bleſſing, through thine infinite mercy in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Meditations concerning ſickneſs.</head>
               <p n="1">1. SIckneſs is ſent either, 1. To try our patience, for the confirming of others; or, 2. That our faith may be found (in the day of the Lord) glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and laudable, to the honour of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41807:15"/> God: or, 3. To correct or amend what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is amiſs in us, or any way offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to our heavenly Father.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sickneſs ſhall turn to our profit, and help us forward in the way that leads to everlaſting life, 1. If we can truly repent us of our ſins. 2. If we can bear our ſickneſs patiently. 3. If we can truſt in Gods mercies aſſuredly. 4. If we can render him humble thanks for his fatherly viſitation. 5. If we can and do ſubmit our ſelves wholly to his good will and pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is no greater comfort to tender Chriſtians, then to be made like to Chriſt, by patient ſuffering ſickneſs, trouble, or death it ſelf: for even he went not up to endleſs joy, but he endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured firſt extremity of pain; he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred not into glory, before he ſuffered and was crucified: ſo our way to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs, is to ſuffer with Chriſt; and our door to everlaſting life, is chearfully to die with and for Chriſt, that we may riſe again from death, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41807:16"/> dwell with him to all eternity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Sickneſs or other afflictions, are not ſignes either of Gods hatred, or of mans reprobation; but rather tokens and pledges of his fatherly love: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtians in the primitive Church were wont to praiſe and bleſs the Lord for afflicting them in this life; ſo did the Apoſtles rejoyce, that they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted worthy to ſuffer for the name, and for the ſake of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the beginning of ſickneſs, and indeed at all times, we are to ſearch deeply into our own hearts; as for all, ſo chiefly for ſome ſecret boſom-ſin. 2. To confeſs our offences to God, and acknowledge our ſelves guilty, even of hell, and of eternal death. 3. We are to remember, that the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is a merciful God, and to cry to him from a faithful and a penitent heart; even as a condemned perſon would do for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, vowing amendment of life, in caſe that health be reſtored.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In our ſtrongeſt health, and before
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41807:16"/> any approach or appearance of death or ſickneſs, we ſhould manifeſt our real and ſincere converſion: 1. In a ſtrict examination what our hearts are, and ſo what our wayes and courſes are. 2. In confeſſing of all our ſins and offences, both open and ſecret, of older time and of later years: then, what duties we have omitted. 3. In ſeeking and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with ſighs unfeigned, and groans of the Spirit, that God will pardon them all, and be reconciled unto us in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. Then will ſickneſs and death it ſelf be moſt welcome to us.</p>
               <p>If ſickneſs have ſeized upon us, it is high time to conſider, That a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preſently carry his luſts, his corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, his hardned heart, his unbelief with him into Heaven: no, it cannot be hoped for; let us repent ere it be too late; let us turn wholly to the Lord, and believe in him with all our hearts. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subpart">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41807:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Remedies againſt Sin.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LEt us not forget, That our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſins and corruptions are to be thought upon with grief, and to be inquired into, whether they be weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in us, or ſtill remaining in their full ſtrength; and whether we do now reſiſt them every day, with more and more force, faithfulneſs and conſtancy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whenſoever we be about the committing of ſin, and finde the grace of God forbidding us, and calling us from it, and yet do run on headlong into it: take heed; for this is no better then crucifying of Chriſt afreſh; and we do no other, then (as the <hi>Jews</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe a gracious Saviour, and take <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabbas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. With our eyes, let us alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold God preſent; with our ears, let us be ever hearing the ſound of that memorable voice, <hi>Ariſe, and come to Judgement;</hi> with our hands, let us be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41807:17"/> ever working and exerciſing that which is good; in our hearts, let us ever lodge the Word of God; and with our feet, let us be conſtantly ſtanding in the courts of the Lords houſe, whenſoever his Word is there preached.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The vows which in Baptiſm I did make by others; that is, To <hi>forſake the devil, the world, and the fleſh,</hi> ſo as not to follow them, nor be led by them: the ſame (for the everlaſting peace of our precious ſouls) we muſt be careful day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and hourly to renew in our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We muſt with diligence avoid all kinde of enticements to that which is evil; as wanton diſcourſe, wandring thoughts, and wicked company; and indeed all the vanities of the world.</p>
               <p n="6">6. We muſt be frequent in humble, faithful, and devout prayer: for none is overcome by a temptation, till he give over holy, conſtant, and zealous praying.</p>
               <p n="7">7. From the bottom of our hearts, let us reſolve conſtantly to embrace, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41807:18"/> to obſerve whatſoever is found to be the will of God; yea, though all the world ſhould repine and perſecute us for it: ſo ſhall our duties and our ſervices be regulated by precept, and winged by promiſes.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A ſoveraign remedy it will prove, to be meditating at all hours, on the hour of death. Obſerve carefully, and do what hath been ſaid diligently, <hi>Et in aeternum non peccabis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Meditations of death.</head>
               <p>THe higheſt delights, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt confidence that is in man, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhift off the importunate and the violent troubles of this adverſary. That example in <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. may ſerve for all. That <hi>Chaldean</hi> Tyrant was carouſing with his Concubines, ſinging trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Carols to the praiſe of his carved gods: yet how was his courage abated, when death writ him a <hi>letter</hi> of <hi>ſummons!</hi> Now no muſick, no pleaſant moving
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41807:18"/> jeſt could remove his deep-ſtruck me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy. O death, how imperious art thou to carnal mindes! Some do fear, not ſo much to be dead, as to die; and ſome do fear, not ſo much to die, as to be dead: whereas, the true Chriſtian (armed only with humble confidence, and holy believing in his future happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) can comfortably encounter him, and in triumph can ſing, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55. <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> &amp;c. Looking chearfully towards Heaven, he can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly ſay, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> That diſſolution is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, which parting the ſoul from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, doth unite both body and ſoul to God. He that ſees the glory of the end, cannot but contemn the hardneſs of the way.</p>
               <p>Of all ſleeps, death may be ſaid to be the ſweeteſt: children begin it to us, ſtrong men ſeek it, and Kings themſelves fall to this centre.</p>
               <p>The pace of death may be ſoft, but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is ſure; and every man (live he never ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41807:19"/> long) is a dying man, till he be dead.</p>
               <p>We ſhould labour to get a particular knowledge and aſſurance, both of our happineſs in death, and of our ſalvation after death. And here remember, that it is of excellent uſe and comfort, to be frequent in receiving of the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>On purpoſe, and in mercy, hath the Lord left, both <hi>our</hi> laſt day, and <hi>the</hi> laſt day, uncertain to us; that we might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes meditate on them, and be every day preparing for them.</p>
               <p>It is the negligent forgetfulneſs of death, that makes our life ſinful, and our death terrible. He that lives holily, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not die unhappily.</p>
               <p>He is moſt certainly bleſſed, that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Lord, what kind of death ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be.</p>
               <p>He only is fearleſs of death, that can ſay upon good ground; Whether I live or die, I am the Lords.</p>
               <p>He that is the true child of God, will never repine or murmur at his rod,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41807:19"/> though it be accompanied with death.</p>
               <p>We may well fear a ſtorm is coming, when the father doth call his children ſo haſtily home.</p>
               <p>Let us then ſay with <hi>Jobs</hi> heart, (<hi>Job</hi> 14.14.) <hi>All the days of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come.</hi> So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Reſolutions againſt the vexations and vanities of the world.</head>
               <p>THe danger of this world, is ſeen in the paucity of ſuch as do paſs well thorow it; and alſo in the multitude of them that periſh in it. All things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are but extream vanity, purchaſing to the owner nothing but anguiſh and vexation of ſpirit: therefore will I bid this vain world adieu; and (that I may loath it, and love God the better) I will be continually meditating on what he hath prepared for me in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and eſpecially on the means of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it; which is, 1. The mercy of God who giveth it. 2. The merit of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41807:20"/> Chriſt that bought it. 3. The holy Goſpel that offereth it. 4. On faith that receiveth it. 5. On the bleſſed Spirit that ſealeth it to my poor ſoul. I will with Chriſt, and by his gracious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, reſolve to endure all for him: all the contempts and perſecutions of the world; all the troubles of the body, all the tortures of death; all the torments of Satan, ſo as I may enjoy my Lord Jeſus Chriſt and his Kingdom. I will renounce and contemn all ſorts of vanities here below, that I may enjoy the preſence of the Lamb; and with him be ſinging <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> everlaſtingly, in the higheſt Heavens. I am weak: but this do I reſolve, in the ſtrength of him, who is the Almighty Lord God.</p>
               <p>I will be neither a fool, nor a rebel; not ignorant from whence my croſſes come, neither will I be impatient in them, knowing that they come from my moſt gracious God: that he hath ſtinted all my miſeries; he hath weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out every dram of my ſorrows; ſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41807:20"/> as all the powers of hell ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to caſt in one ſcruple more then God hath allotted for me. We know, that even ſavage creatures will endure to be ſmitten by their Maſters, and yet be ready to tear ſtrangers in pieces: ſhall I then ſtruggle with him that made me, and framed and moderated the whole world, when he is pleaſed to ſmite me? No, we ſhould learn and remember, that our extremities in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, are Gods beſt oportunities to ſhew mercy.</p>
               <p>I will have no plot, but againſt hells policy: I will have no deſigne, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſins ſtratagems: I will learn how I am to act in this life, to my God fidelity, to my Prince loyalty, to my friends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, to my ſelf humility: ſo ſhall I be kept from future falls, and alſo be guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from preſent fears: for this we are aſſured of, that God hath either the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of a providence, or the Ark of a promiſe, or the faithfulneſs of his power, or the all-ſufficiency of his own
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41807:21"/> grace, for a retirement to his people, in times of greateſt ſtorms and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>PART II. Meditations at the firſt Sickning.</head>
            <div n="1" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> A Prayer in time of Sickneſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In their affliction</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 54, 6.) <hi>they will ſeek me early.</hi> So <hi>Egypt</hi>'s burden made <hi>Iſrael</hi> cry to God: ſo <hi>David</hi>'s troubles made him to pray: ſo <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s ſickneſs cauſed him to weep: ſo miſery drove the Prodigal home: and ſo let me in this my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſincerely and believingly, haſten to my God in humble ſupplication.</p>
               <p>OH moſt righteous Judge; and yet in Jeſus Chriſt, my gracious Father: I a poor wretched ſinner, do here return unto thee with the Prodigal, that was annoyed with want and hunger; and do humbly acknowledge, that this pain and ſickneſs is none other then the juſt ſtroke
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41807:21"/> of thine own hand: but though my ſins have been many and great, yet in wrath thou doſt remember mercy; for thy corrections have been eaſie and few: I have deſerved to be ſmitten with ſome fearful death, ſo as to have periſhed in my ſins; but thou, O Lord, beſides the dictates of thy heavenly Word and boly Spirit, doſt now viſit me in mercy; giving me by this ſickneſs, not only warning to conſider, and time to repent me of all my manifold tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, but alſo opportunity to ſue to the throne of grace for pardon; ſo as I do not apprehend this viſitation as a ſign of thy heavy diſpleaſure againſt me, but rather as an aſſured pledge and token of thy fatherly kindneſs; by this temporal chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to draw me to the judging of my ſelf, to be humbled for all my offendings, to abhor my ſelf in duſt and aſhes, ſo as not to be condemned with the world: for thy holy Word hath taught us, That thou ſcourgeſt every ſon that thou receiveſt; and that if I do patiently and believingly endure thy chaſtiſing hand, thou doſt offer thy ſelf as a tender father to relieve me. O Lord, how full of mercy and compaſſion is thy nature, that haſt dealt ſo graciouſly with me, in affording to me a long time of health and proſperity; ſuch, as few have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more! I do confeſs, O Lord, that thou moſt juſtly doſt afflict my body with ſickneſs; for my ſoul before, was ſick of long proſperity, and even ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited with health, &amp; eaſe, &amp; peace, and plenty, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41807:22"/> fulneſs of bread. A wretched ſinner I have been, void of all goodneſs by nature, and full of evil works by cuſtom: but ſeeing thy mercy is above all, I beſeech thee heavenly father, in Jeſus Chriſt, for his ſake, and for his meritorious ſuffering, and according to the multitude of thy mercies, caſt me not out of thy gracious preſence, neither reward me after my iniquities. As thou art the helper of the helpleſs, and the God of all conſolation, to ſuch as truſt in thee: as thou art pleaſed to lay this ſickneſs upon me; ſo let it work that good effect which thou in thy great mercy doſt intend. And good Lord, ſend thy holy Spirit into my heart, by which this and all other thy diſpenſations may be ſanctified to me; that I may uſe the ſame as a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in thy School, whereby to be taught, both the greatneſs of my miſery and wants, and alſo the fulneſs of thy riches and mercy, in the Lord Chriſt; to be ſo humbled at the one, as not to deſpair of the other. Grant that I may renounce all confidence in my ſelf, and in every other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or means; ſo as only to put the whole truſt of my preſervation and ſalvation in thy boundleſs mercy. And for as much, O Lord, as thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt how weak a veſſel I am, full of frailty, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and imperfection; and how by nature I am froward and impatient under the leaſt croſs, and under the lighteſt affliction: Do thou, O Lord, (who art the giver of all good gifts) indue me
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41807:22"/> with heavenly grace, with holy patience, and with godly fortitude; ſo as quietly to reſign up my ſelf, even body and ſoul, to what thou ſhalt appoint for me. And of thy tender mercy, lay no more upon me, then thou ſhalt pleaſe to enable me comfortably to bear. Strengthen me by thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace, that during this ſickneſs, and in all other times of affliction, I may behave my ſelf in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and meekneſs, and faith, and quiet repoſe, in the ſight and preſence of thoſe friends or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants that ſhall come or be about me: and alſo, that I may both thankfully receive, and readily improve, all ſuch ſeaſonable counſel, and heavenly conſolation, and holy direction, as ſhall proceed from them. And likewiſe, that I may ſhew ſuch Chriſtianly example of childe-like patience; and withal, may give forth ſuch godly leſſons of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly comfort, as may be both apparent argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſure teſtimonies of my holy profeſſion; and alſo of uſe and inſtruction to them, how they are to behave themſelves in the day of their viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I do confeſs, O Lord, that in regard of my great provocations, I have deſerved both ſickneſs and death it ſelf; and I do now deſire no longer to live, then to reform my evil life, and in ſome better meaſure to ſet forth thy glory: but if thou haſt, according to thy eternal decree, appointed by this ſickneſs, to call for me out of this tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory life; Lord, help me willingly to reſign my ſelf
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41807:23"/> into thy hands, ſaying, <hi>Thy bleſſed will be done;</hi> only I do moſt humbly beſeech thee, even for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, who is the Son of thy love, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all my ſins, and in him to be reconciled to me; and ſo to prepare my poor ſoul, that by a lively faith, and unfeigned repentance, ſhe may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to yield up her ſelf when thou ſhalt be pleaſed to call for her. O holy Father, thou art the hearer of prayers; hear thou in heaven theſe my weak ſupplications, and in this my ſickneſs (which is like to increaſe upon me) be pleaſed to ſhew thy Almighty power and goodneſs: Teach my heart in holy believing to ſay, Whether I live, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I die, I am Chriſts, and Chriſt is mine; and he ſhall be advantage to me, both here and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and for ever. To him, with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all honour, and glory, and power, and dominion, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord will be a refuge,</hi> (Pſa. <hi>9.9.) in time of trouble. Hear me, O Lord my God,</hi> (Pſal. <hi>13.3, 5.) that I ſleep not in death: for my truſt is in thy mercy, and my heart is joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in thy ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subpart">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:41807:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Concerning Prayer.</head>
               <p>CHriſt, and God, and all, is laid out for the good of the godly: they may go to God with holy boldneſs, and tell him wherein they are troubled, pained, afflicted, oppreſſed. If we ask great things from God, he is well pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it; but if we ask riches, and honour, and worldly preferment, theſe are the low things of the footſtool, and they are often in mercy denyed: let us therefore of God, ask peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, pardon of ſin; let us crave power to overcome our luſts, ſtrength to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand temptations, joy in the holy Ghoſt, and grace to glorifie our dear Redeemer, both in doing and in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. God hath moſt aſſuredly all good things lying ready by him; only he looks that Prayer ſhould fetch them from him. Now obſerve: When our great Maſter Chriſt would give us a perfect pattern of Prayer, both for matter and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41807:24"/> for manner, he there windes up, and wraps up all with a concluſion, which conſiſts of certain reaſons, to perſwade our heavenly Father to hear our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; or at leaſt, to aſſure our ſouls that he doth, and that he will hear them: and theſe reaſons have a certain influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence into all and every one of the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Thine is the Kingdom:</hi> for this reaſon we do expect, that as a good King thou wilt receive us, and anſwer our petitions. It is thy concernment, as a King, to have thine honour advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; for this reaſon, <hi>Hallow thine own Name;</hi> glorifie it in the Church; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance thy <hi>Will</hi> in it; ſuſtain us thy <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;</hi> pardon our <hi>Offences;</hi> keep and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend us <hi>from all evil,</hi> eſpecially our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemies: <hi>for thine is the Power;</hi> ſuch power as Kings do want; but thou art fully able, 1. To exalt thine own Name. 2. To extend thy Kingdom over all. 3. To fit us to do thy Will. 4. To miniſter to our Neceſſities. 5. To par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our Sins. 6. To preſerve us from,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41807:24"/> and to deliver us out of all evil; and then, <hi>thine is the Glory;</hi> the hallowing of thy Name is the chief part of thy glory; thy Kingdom is the prime place of thy glory. And herein art thou glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, that is, when we ſet forth thy praiſe; when we obey thy will; when thou provideſt for thy people; when thou forgiveſt their ſins; when thou comforteſt them in their calamities: So do we truſt and hope, that thou wilt do all theſe things for us.</p>
               <p>Take heed; for if in our prayers we come to God, with a guilty defiled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; with cold affections; with dead ſpirits, not departing from iniquity, and without a pure heart: This is howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not praying.</p>
               <p>Prayer, by good Chriſtians, hath been ſtiled and eſteemed the key of Heaven, and the confuſion of hell; the ſtandard of our ſpiritual warfare; the conſervation of our peace; the bridle of our impatience; the guardian of our temperance; the ſeal of chaſtity; the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41807:25"/> of offenders; the conſolation of the afflicted; and the Paſport of the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thus the juſt do live and die in prayer.</p>
               <p>A Chriſtian without prayer, may be compared to a Bee without a ſting; which can make neither wax nor honey.</p>
               <p>A true Chriſtian makes prayer not only his lock and key of the day, but his bolt at night; yea, his very meals and recreations: for this it was, that the primitive Chriſtians were called the crickets of the night; becauſe when ſleep did fail, their hearts were lifted up in conſtant ejaculatory prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Meditations at firſt ſickning.</head>
               <p>WIth one croſs, be it of ſickneſs or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affliction, God doth uſually work two cures: 1. By chaſtiſement for ſins paſt. 2. By preventing of ſins to come; ſo as we may ſay with the Prophet, <hi>Before I was afflicted I went aſtray; but now</hi> (thy grace aſſiſting) <hi>I will keep thy ſtatutes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41807:25"/>2. God ſends ſickneſs, and other affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to ſeal to us our adoption: <hi>For every childe whom God loveth, he chaſtiſeth; and ſuffereth the wicked ſtill to continue in their ſins without correction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. God ſends ſickneſs to wean our hearts from the love of the world, and of worldly vanities; and to cauſe us more early to deſire, and more earneſtly to long for Heaven.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Of all afflictions and croſſes, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be held to come moſt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from the hand of God, and that becauſe of ſin.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By ſickneſs and affliction, God doth exerciſe his children, &amp; the graces which he beſtows upon them: he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by tryeth and refineth our faith, to make it to ſhine more clear; he thereby ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth us up to pray more frequently, and more zealouſly. He ſees what patience we have learned all this while in his School: and ſo concerning our hope in Chriſt; our love to the glorious Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; our charity to our Chriſtian bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren, and the like.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:41807:26"/>6. Sanctified ſickneſs and affliction is a ſingular help to further us in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; and by unfeigned ſorrow and true repentance, to drive us home to our heavenly Father in holy believing.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Sickneſs and affliction do work in us, not only Chriſtianly love and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but pity and compaſſion alſo towards our brethren; ſo as to have a fellow-feeling with them in all their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p n="8">8. God doth many times make uſe of our ſickneſs, and other afflictions, not only as means, and as examples, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to manifeſt to others the faith, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and other graces that he hath beſtowed upon us; but alſo by the ſame, to ſtrengthen and to encourage others, that have not yet received ſo great a meaſure of faith and of aſſurance as we have done.</p>
               <p n="9">9. By ſickneſs and afflictions, God worketh us to a conformity of the image of his Son Jeſus Chriſt; who being the Captain of our ſalvation, was
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41807:26"/> made perfect through ſuffering.</p>
               <p n="10">10. God ſendeth ſickneſs, that the godly may thereby be humbled, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their own condition and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and that God may be glorified, by a gracious delivering them out of all their troubles, when in ſincerity they call upon him for his help and ſuccour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Directions and Conſolations in time of Sickneſs and Death.</head>
               <p>LEt every Chriſtian upon his ſick bed, not only with patience look for death, but with comfort alſo; and that for theſe reaſons: 1. Becauſe the death of every member of Chriſt (as well as of others) is foreſeen and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the ſpecial decree and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God. 2. Reaſon is taken from the promiſe of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the dead that die in the Lord; for they ſhall reſt from their labours, and their works follow them.</hi> 3. He that dyeth in Chriſt, his ſoul and his body are really
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41807:27"/> united to Chriſt, according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace. 4. God hath alſo promiſed his gracious &amp; ſpecial preſence to ſuch ſick and dying perſons as do belong to him: ſo he ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.1. <hi>Fear not, for I have redeemed thee: I have called thee by thy name, thou art mine; when thou paſſeſt thorow the waters, I will be with thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A little blaſt of ſickneſs doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times become mortal, and we are many a time carried away in that blaſt: and if we ſhould hold out a while longer, we do but daily conſume and moulder away with old age, till we return to our duſt; and at laſt do become but a coffin for the worms.</p>
               <p>Let not a dying man think on the pangs of death, which may perhaps be light and ſhort; but let him wholly fix his thoughts, and the eye of his faith, upon that bleſſed eſtate of eternal life, which Jeſus Chriſt hath purchaſed for him.</p>
               <p>In the buſineſs of ſickneſs, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of death, lay aſide all curious
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41807:27"/> ſpeculations of Gods unſearchable counſels; all cogitations and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of works, of traditions of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, yea, and of the Law of God too; and run ſtrait to the manger, embrace the babe Chriſt in thine arms, yea, in thy ſoul: behold him as he was born, growing up, converſant amongſt men; as teaching, dying, riſing again, aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above the heavens, and having power above all things. This thought, this ſight, will make thee to ſhake off all troubles and terrors, as the Sun dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth away the clouds.</p>
               <p>We muſt live in the world, as in a ſtrange Country, where we are every day taking our farewel, being (as in ſickneſs) alwayes ready to depart; and becauſe the inſtant of our departing is uncertain, we ſhould wait for it every hour. The wiſe Chriſtian, that heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the minutes of his breathing, can never be ſurpriſed when the hour of his laſt ſigh doth ſtrike.</p>
               <p>Our duty in ſickneſs, or any other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41807:28"/> is to inquire and finde out the cauſe; if it be for ſin, to humble our ſelves, to juſtifie God, to turn to him, to ſubmit to his will, to ſeek his favour, to minde our own duty, and to live by faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> A Prayer, before taking of Phyſick.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, give me perfect love to thy heavenly Majeſty, that I may not delight in any thing at all but thee; nor look for any other ſafety at all but in thee; nor ſeek for any other help but from thee.</p>
               <p>O moſt holy and moſt merciful Father in Jeſus Chriſt; who art the Lord both of health and of ſickneſs; who killeſt and makeſt alive; who bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt down to the grave, and raiſeſt up again: I do humbly come unto thee, unto thee, as to the only Phyſician of Phyſicians; who canſt as eaſily cure my ſoul from ſin, as my body from ſickneſs. I do not at this time deſire either life or death, but do wholly yield up my ſelf to thy bleſſed will: death indeed is the reward of ſin: for <hi>ſin, when it is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, bringeth forth death:</hi> yet ſeeing thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious providence (while life remaineth) hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed means for thy diſtreſſed children to uſe, (and by the lawful and thankful uſe of it, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41807:28"/> humble ſeeking to thee for it) to expect thy father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſing, for healing of their diſtempers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring them to their health; In this my neceſſity, I do apply my ſelf to the Phyſitian, and am entring upon the courſe which he ſhall preſcribe: O Lord help me, that I may caſt my ſelf wholly upon thee. Teach me to call faithfully upon thy great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Name for a bleſſing upon it: It is thou, O Lord, that didſt recover <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> that didſt cleanſe the Lepers, that didſt reſtore the woman with the bloody Iſſue; and it is from thy great mercy, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power, and gracious providence alone, that I expect deliverance out of this malady: Oh be pleaſed, of thine infinite goodneſs, to ſanctifie to me this Phyſick that I ſhall now take; and ſo to proſper the ſame, that (if it be thy bleſſed will and pleaſure) it may remove this ſickneſs, and take away this pain, and reſtore me to my former health and ſtrength: but if thou haſt appointed this ſickneſs to draw me nearer to thy ſelf, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant obedience and holy dependance upon thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Majeſty: or, if thou haſt ſent this ſickneſs as thy meſſenger, to call me out of this mortal life; then help me to ſay with integrity &amp; ſincerity, <hi>Thy will be done;</hi> &amp; enable me with cheerfulneſs to ſubmit to thy divine pleaſure. And this I do humbly &amp; moſt earneſtly beg of thee, to aſſiſt me with thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for the increaſe of faith and patience in this my day of trouble. O Lord, let thy tender and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41807:29"/> fatherly compaſſion be never wanting to me; but in the midſt of all extremities, be pleaſed to ſupport me with thy continual help, that I may both willingly and chriſtianly reſigne up my ſoul (as the price of thine own blood) into thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hands and bleſſed protection. Grant this, O Lord, to thy poor ſervant, and whatever elſe in thine infinite wiſdom and goodneſs thou knoweſt to be neceſſary for my preſent weak condition; ſuch as may tend to my everlasting comfort, and thine eternal glory. All this I beg, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake; to whom with thee and thy holy Spirit, be aſcribed all Majeſty, power, and glory, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subpart">
               <head>VI. A Prayer before Phyſick is on working.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Holy Father in Jeſus Chriſt, when in my weakneſs the time ſhall come, that Satan ſhall maliciouſly accuſe me; when my unquiet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall bear witneſs againſt me; when world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advantages ſhall forſake me; and when every creature, and every thing ſhall ſeem to ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt me, and that for my manifold, and my reiterated ſins againſt thy heavenly Majeſty; then do thou (who art the God of all conſolation) do thou ſtrengthen me in my moſt holy faith, ſo that If all not at all from thee, though every thing doth ſeem to flee from me. But, Lord, I beſeech thee,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41807:29"/> let thy fulneſs ſupply my wants, let thy mercy do away my offendings, let thy holy Spirit prepare my ſoul for thy heavenly appointment; let thy merits, O moſt bleſſed Saviour, enrich my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty: Oh, let thy dear and precious blood waſh away all the ſpots and ſtains of my poor polluted ſoul. And Lord, be pleaſed at this time, to vouchſafe a bleſſing upon the Phyſick which I have now taken, for removing of my pain, and recovery of my health; and if thou ſhalt afford this mercy to thy poor creature, then Lord, I beſeech thee grant grace, that the ſame health and eaſe may be imployed and improved for the glory of thy great Name, and for the preſent comfort and final ſalvation of my poor ſoul. And all this I beg, in, and by, and through the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of thee my bleſſed Redeemer, Jeſus Chriſt; to whom, with the heavenly Father and the holy Spirit, be given, as is moſt due, bleſſing, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory, and power, both now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Six Medicines to cure the fear of Death.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe <hi>firſt Medicine,</hi> is contempt of the world: For, 1. It will be an eaſie thing to die, when our hearts are once
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41807:30"/> freed from the love of earthly things; therefore ſhould we ſhun the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much care and buſineſs of the world, and ſtudy to be quiet, &amp; to meddle only with our own matters, and to draw them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to as narrow a ſcantling as our calling will permit. 2. We ſhould avoid (as much as may be) the ſociety of the worlds favourites, that admire nothing but what this world affords; that know no other happineſs but that of this life, whereby our hearts are too much intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled. 3. We ſhould ſort our ſelves with ſuch Chriſtians, as do practiſe as well as praiſe the contempt of the world, and by whoſe <hi>example</hi> &amp; <hi>diſcourſe</hi> we may be brought to be in love with Heaven. 4. We ſhould daily obſerve, to what things in the world our hearts are moſt carried out, and by fervent ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to ſtrive with the Lord to ſuppreſs them. 5. We ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes pondering in our thoughts, thoſe things which may ſhew us the vanity of the world, and the vileneſs and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorineſs
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41807:30"/> of the beſt things which the world affords.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſecond Medicine,</hi> or cure of the fear of death, is <hi>Mortification.</hi> 1. We muſt throughly mortifie all our boſom and beloved ſins; our ſins muſt die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we die, otherwiſe our dying will be dangerous to us: it is the love and the delight that men take in ſin, which makes them ſo much afraid to die; or elſe it may be the remembrance of ſome filthy ſin committed, which doth terrifie the conſcience; therefore we muſt make ſure of our repentance. Now he may be ſaid truly to repent himſelf of all ſin, that allows not in himſelf any ſin. 2. We muſt here add the care of an upright, and of an unreproveable converſation: A marvellous help and encouragement it is to die in peace, when a man doth live without offence, and upon juſt ground can plead the integrity of a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>third Medicine,</hi> or cure againſt the fear of death, is <hi>Aſſurance.</hi> We
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41807:31"/> ſhould be diligent to get aſſurance, both of Gods favour, and of our own calling and election; for hereby will an entrance be given into the heavenly Kingdom. <hi>Simeon</hi> could willingly die, when his eyes had ſeen his ſalvation: the full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of faith doth wonderfully eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the heart, and guard it from the fear of death, and alſo doth breed a longing deſire to come to Chriſt. St. <hi>Paul</hi> can be confident, when he is able to ſay, <hi>I know whom I have believed;</hi> and, <hi>I am aſſured, that he is able to keep that which I have committed to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>fourth Medicine,</hi> is <hi>ſetting our houſe in Order.</hi> A great part of the fear and trouble of mens mindes on their ſick beds is over, when (with good delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and advice) they have ſettled their Eſtates, and diſpoſed of their worldly affairs. This is a matter not to be put off to a time of languiſhing ſickneſs, when the trouble of it breeds diſquiet to their mindes; when their memory and underſtanding is diſabled; when this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41807:31"/> neceſſary duty of preparing for death is thereby hindered, if not wholly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>fifth Medicine,</hi> is, 1. A frequent meditation of <hi>Death.</hi> We muſt learn to die daily; for this will leſſen, yea, it will remove the fear of dying: Oh, this remembrance of our latter end, and learning to number our days, is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable rule for to practiſe. 2. We ſhould begin this exerciſe betimes. In this, lay the commendation of thoſe wiſe Virgins, and ſo of <hi>Job,</hi> who reſolved to be alwayes waiting till his change ſhould come.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>ſixth Medicine</hi> againſt the fear of death, is holy and hearty <hi>Prayer.</hi> Becauſe our natures are extreamly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, there is a neceſſity of frequent and faithful prayer to be uſed, which will never fail us in whatſoever is fit for us: It is that which God will not deny to thoſe that ask it in ſincerity, &amp; in the Name of the Lord Jeſus; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a thing which Chriſt our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41807:32"/> Saviour did eſpecially aim at in his own death; namely, to deliver us from the power, yea, from the fear of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Rules to make our Calling and Election ſure.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE muſt be diligent hearers of Gods holy Word; for <hi>faith cometh by hearing:</hi> what is the reaſon, that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do waver and wander out of the way that is called <hi>Holy?</hi> Is it not, becauſe they are idle hearers? is it not, becauſe they will not be at the pains to hear ſo carefully, as to finde what their caſe and condition is, and what it doth require?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Rule.</hi> We muſt frequently receive the Lords Supper: even every experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced Chriſtian is able to tell us, That this holy Ordinance hath (by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and bleſſing of God) a very notable confirming and eſtabliſhing power in it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Rule.</hi> If we would have our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and our Election to be made ſure,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41807:32"/> then muſt we ſue to God, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did, that the Lord would increaſe our faith; for unleſs Gods Spirit do teſtifie together with our ſpirit, we can never come to any aſſurance of faith, nor to any certainty of ſalvation: <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apollo</hi> may water; but it is God alone that muſt give the increaſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Rule.</hi> If we deſire to make our Calling and Election ſure, we muſt be frequent in meditating of Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as they are ſet forth in his holy Word; and accordingly we muſt try our eſtate, by the particular marks which are peculiar to Gods elect.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Rule.</hi> If we would make our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election ſure, we muſt be plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful in good works: for, who are they which lay up for themſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come, and ſo laying hold upon eternal life, but ſuch as are rich in good works? We are not only to repent, and to turn to God; but to do works meet for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:41807:33"/>6. <hi>Rule.</hi> That we may make our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and our Election ſure, Let us always be making our deſires known to the Lord in our humble ſupplications, that he will eſtabliſh us in the moſt holy faith; that believing in him, we may remain immoveable; neither in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to forget him, or in adverſity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of him.</p>
               <p>And thus we ſee the way to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable departure out of this life: The Lord give us grace to chufe this way; that ſo by our death, we may both glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God, bring comfort and good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to our friends, and everlaſting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to our own ſouls. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Againſt doubtings of Gods mercy.</head>
               <p n="1">1. LEt us confeſs, even all our ſins to God. 2. Let us be careful to make ſatisfaction to whomſoever in this life we have wronged, be it in goods or in good name; without which there can be no true repentance, and ſo no ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41807:33"/> 3. Call upon God for mercy and pardon in the Lord Jeſus, and labour for faith in him; and then in the midſt of pain and doubting, remember, that the way to Heaven is by the gates of Hell. 4. Get a lively faith in Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo tarry the Lords leiſure; be ſtrong, and he ſhall comfort our hearts. 5. In the ſence of our greateſt ſins, let us remember, that Gods mercies do ſhine more in pardoning great offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, then ſmall tranſgreſſors; for where ſin aboundeth, there doth grace rejoyce to abound much more. 6. God did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſake any, till they did firſt forſake him. 7. God calleth all (even ſinners that are heavy laden) to be refreſhed: the leaſt drop of Chriſts blood, is of more merit to procure Gods mercy for our ſalvation, then all our ſins whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, can be of force to procure his wrath to our condemnation. 8. Let our ſins be of never ſo long continuance, or of never ſo heavy a weight; let us but repent and believe, and then the blood
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41807:34"/> of Jeſus Chriſt will cleanſe us from all ſins. 9. Though our vows and promiſes of new obedience have not been exactly performed; yet upon our tears of true repentance, through faith in the Lord Jeſus, we ſhall be recovered as oft as we are wounded to death by ſin: for our ſalvation is grounded, not upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of our obedience, but upon the firmneſs of Gods gracious Covenant with us in Chriſt Jeſus. 10. No ſin, though never ſo great, ought to drive any Chriſtian into deſpair, ſeeing, if he believe and repent, he hath the pardon of all his ſins confirmed to him; and that, 1. By the Word of God: <hi>At what time ſoever a ſinner repenteth, and turneth to the Lord, he will blot out all his offences,</hi> &amp;c. 2. By the Oath of God: <hi>As I live</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I deſire not the death of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</hi> No ſin doth debar a man from God, but only incredulity and impenitency. Believe it, O thou drooping ſoul; our unfeigned deſire to repent, is as pleaſing and as acceptable to God, as our perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteſt repentance can be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:41807:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Reading of Chapters, or portions of Scripture.</head>
               <p>REad carefully and conſiderately theſe Chapters following, or part of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26, 27, and 28 Chapters, being he Hiſtory of our Saviours Paſſion and Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> the 2 Chapter. <hi>Rom.</hi> the 7 and 8 Chapt. <hi>Heb.</hi> the 11 and 12 Chapt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41807:35"/>
            <head>PART III. Meditations at growing Weak.</head>
            <div n="1" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> A Prayer upon danger of Death.</head>
               <p>OH moſt glorious and moſt gracious Lord God, thy providence doth extend to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt parts of the earth, and thy favourable beams do ſhine upon the chief of ſinners; be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to caſt thy compaſſionate eye upon me, whom thou haſt brought to the bed of ſickneſs: juſt it is with thee thus to correct me, yea, to deſtroy me, body and ſoul: ſeeing I have ſo grievouſly offended thee, I will not, I dare not, I cannot plead againſt thee; it is my duty rather to magnifie thy mercy, that haſt ſpared me ſo long, and art now pleaſed ſo graciouſly and ſo fatherly to chaſtiſe me, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free to thy juſtice to cut me off, and to deliver me over to the Prince of darkneſs. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy I am, I do confeſs, of this acceſs to thy gracious preſence, in that I have formerly been ſo careleſs thereof; yet ſeeing thou art ever wont, more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the truth of thine own promiſe, then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of thoſe that pray unto thee; ſeeing thou vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeſt to ſtile thy ſelf, <hi>The hearer of Prayer,</hi> I beſeech thee, hearken to the humble ſuit of thy poor ſupplicant. Lord ſanctifie to me this preſent
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41807:35"/> ſickneſs; let it be as thy School, in which I may learn more ſincerely to honour thee, and truly to know my ſelf. Make me ſeriouſly ſenſible, that all this, and whatever elſe thou ſhalt now lay upon me, are but the fruits of ſin; and that as ſickneſs makes way for death, ſo death is the fore-runner, either of eternal ſalvation or condemnation: Lord bleſs this meditation ſo to me, that I may make it my chief buſineſs to ſeek aſſurance of my being reconciled to thy heavenly Majeſty. To this end, Lord, give me a deep apprehenſion, and a ſenſible underſtanding of my fore-paſſed tranſgreſſions: Lord, take from me all blindneſs of mind, all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of ſpirit, all inclination to flatter or to ſooth up my ſelf, ſo as to leſſen either the number or the quality of my offences. Cauſe me to break, and even to plough up my heart, to ſearch and to try my wayes; that ſo, out of the truth, and the abundance of the ſence and feeling of my ſins, I may pour out a moſt plentiful, and a moſt ſincere confeſſion before thee. Help me to conſider, that it is a vain thing to ſeek to cover mine iniquities from thine all-ſeeing eye; therefore let me rather lay open my moſt ſecret ſins before thee, with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and true contrition, this being a ſafe way to finde mercy and pardon at thy gracious hands. O then, be pleaſed to ſtrengthen my weak faith, that I may from the ſight of my ſinful condition, lay hold upon the infinite merits of my bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41807:36"/> and with all humility caſt all my burden upon him, who by his moſt precious blood hath purged away all ſin and all uncleanneſs: And becauſe, O Lord, I am full of imperfections, there being in my nature much weakneſs to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, much frowardneſs to repine, and great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to rebel againſt thy holy Ordinances, be graciouſly pleaſed to furniſh me with neceſſary graces, and with ſuch heavenly gifts as thou in thine infinite wiſdom and goodneſs doſt know to be fit for my preſent eſtate; endue me with patience, cheerfully to bear whatſoever thou ſhalt pleaſe to lay upon me, meekly ſubmitting to thy moſt holy appointment. Aſſure me, that thou who knoweſt whereof I am made, and that I am but poor duſt, wilt not preſs me with more then thou wilt ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me to bear. Grant, good Lord, that the hope of the glory which ſhall be revealed, may be more ſtrong in me, and more powerful upon me that all things in this world may be vile and worthleſs in compariſon of it; make me to be comfortably ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the counſel and caution which my Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian friends ſhall in tender affection indeavour to adminiſter to my fainting ſoul; and ſo likewiſe, make me able, willing and ready to ſpeak and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver ſomething of piety and of profit to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as in my ſickneſs ſhall be about me. Lord, put into me charitable thoughts and holy affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards all people, and that I may be both wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41807:36"/> to ſatisfie whereſoever I have failed in my duty, and alſo ready to remit whereſoever I have received greateſt injury or indignity. Oh holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Jeſus Chriſt, prepare me, I humbly beſeech thee, and enable me towards my laſt conflict: Oh help and defend me, and by thy Almighty power preſerve me from and againſt the aſſaults and the deceits of Satan, who at ſuch a time as this, is moſt buſie to deſtroy thy poor creatures: grant, that notwithſtanding his mortal malice, I may keep my ſelf cloſe to thee, and conſtantly and faithfully to reſolve, that though thou ſlay me, yet to put my whole truſt in thee: And ſeeing that ſickneſs (ſo great is thy compaſſion to poor creatures) doth not always exerciſe its full power upon our weak frail bodies, Oh Lord vouchſafe unto me that underſtanding and ſpiritual pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as to make a holy uſe of every ſmall breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of every little time of eaſe, which in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy thou ſhalt be pleaſed to afford unto me, ſo as to gather ſtrength and reſolution against the time of greater pain and anguiſh. I beſeech thee be ſtill bringing to my remembrance thoſe evidences of thy former favours, and thoſe comfortable examples and inſtructions which I have from time to time found in thy holy Word, ſo as to be thereby quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and refreſhed, and ſo as to know and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge; and ſo finde ſpiritual comfort in my greateſt need:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41807:37"/> And as the danger of death ſhall increaſe upon me, ſo let heavenly rejoycing and holy deſires increaſe in me: Oh, let me groan earneſtly, and deſire to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, upon good ground believing, that thou haſt made him to be ſin (that knew no ſin) for me, that I might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him. Now Lord, hear and help, and do for me thy poor creature, according to thine everlaſting love, and mercy, and compaſſion, in the ſame my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Conſolations concerning Death.</head>
               <p>I Owe to God a death, even as his dear Son did die for me: Ever ſince I was born, I have been ſailing to this Haven, and have or ſhould have been gathering reſolution, ſtrength and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to ſweeten and to comfort this hour; therefore I ſhall not, I will not (the Lord aſſiſting me) now be one of thoſe gueſts that would not come to the banquet when they were invited. What hurt is there in going to Paradiſe? I ſhall loſe nothing but the ſence of evil,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41807:37"/> and I ſhall preſently reap greater joys then I now feel pain; for my head is in Heaven already, to aſſure me that my body and ſoul ſhall follow after. <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> why ſhould I fear that which I would not eſcape, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it gives entrance to my chiefeſt happineſs? and I cannot have it unleſs I go to it. Every man would be willing to paſs thorow Hell to Heaven; but if I march only thorow death, I ſuffer leſs then I would ſuffer for God: my pains do not diſmay me, becauſe I travel to bring forth life, even eternal life; my ſins do not afright me, becauſe I have Chriſt, the Captain of our ſalvation, for my Redeemer: The Judge doth not aſtoniſh me, becauſe the Son of the Judge is my prevailing advocate; the Devil doth not amaze me, becauſe the holy Angels do pitch their tents round about me; the grave doth not grieve me becauſe it was my Lords bed; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and the Apoſtles are my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners; every man is gone before me,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41807:38"/> or elſe he muſt come after me: if it pleaſe the Lord to receive me into his heavenly manſions before others which have ſerved him better, the more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thankfulneſs do I owe unto him. And leſt (by putting off my repentance till this hour, I ſhould be cut off if) I ſhould die ſuddenly, Behold how my gracious God in his merciful providence, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent my ruine and deſtruction, doth call me to himſelf by a lingring ſickneſs, which ſtayeth me till I be ready, and prepareth me for my departure, and makes me (by theſe wholſome pains) weary of this too-much-beloved world, leſt I ſhould too unwillingly part with it, and ſo be like them whoſe death is their damnation. Thus the Lord loveth me while he ſmiteth me, ſo that his ſtripes become plaiſters to me; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore who ſhall love him, if I ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe him? who ſhall praiſe him, if I ſhould diſhonour him? This is my whole duty now, to ſtrengthen my weak body with my believing heart, to be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41807:38"/> contented with whatſoever God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for me, until I can glorifie him, or he ſhall glorifie me: If I live, I live to ſacrifice; if I die, I ſhall then die a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; for his mercy is above mine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And now, if I ſhould fear death, it would be a ſigne that I had neither faith nor hope, as I have profeſſed, but that I doubted of Gods truth (in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes) whether or no he will forgive his poor dejected penitent: but it is my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let him do with me whatſoever ſeemeth good in his ſight. Then come Lord Jeſus, for thy ſervant cometh; I am willing, Lord, help my unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; I believe, Lord, help my unbelief; make me ready to receive thee: Then come, then come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Againſt impatience in ſickneſs.</head>
               <p>LEt us conſider, 1. That our ſins have deſerved far greater pains then we do ſuffer, even the pains of Hell.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41807:39"/> 2. That God hath in mercy determined the day of our deliverance: The number of our tears (ſhed for the diſhonouring of God) are regiſtred in his book. 3. Let us think on the bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> who (as ſoon as he ſaw Chriſt) forgot his wounds, and the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the grave, and ſweetly yielded up his ſoul into the arms of his bleſſed Saviour: ſo let us do; let us forget our pain, and meditate on the wounds of Chriſt Jeſus; let us be faithful to the death, and ſo receive a crown of life. 4. As we have alwayes prayed. <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thy will be done;</hi> ſo now let us yield willingly to whatſoever his holy will is; elſe we diſſemble with God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our own ſouls. 5. Remember, that the rod, be it of ſickneſs or any other affliction, is in the hands of a merciful Father. 6. Believe, that all things (though ſeemingly moſt ſharp) ſhall work together for the beſt, if we love and fear him; and that nothing, neither life, nor death, nor any creature, ſhall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41807:39"/> ever be able to ſeparate between us and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. 7. That God doth uſe this chaſtiſement of the body, but as a Medicine for the curing of our ſin-ſick ſouls, by drawing us to our great Phyſician, by true repentance, godly patience, and holy believing. 8. The greateſt pains that we can feel in our greateſt extremity, are not to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with thoſe grievous dolours which our bleſſed Saviour did undergo for us: how then can we be impatient at any ſmart that he ſhall lay upon us? 9. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this our ſuffering doth befal us, but what the holy men of God have felt, and moſt patiently undergone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, and are now in poſſeſſion of everlaſting joys in the higheſt Heavens. 10. God hath not given us over to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable enemies, but (as a loving and tender-hearted Father) doth pleaſe to keep us in his own moſt gracious hands, laying upon us no more then what he ſhall ſee and know to be moſt needful and profitable for us. 11. Laſtly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41807:40"/> and conſider it with comfort, How death (if it ſhall follow ſickneſs) will deliver us from a weak, frail, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble body, which is but a living priſon of the ſoul, and a lively inſtrument of ſin; and how death doth ſet us free to enjoy the liberty of the Saints in glory. To conclude: If we love holineſs when it is compaſſed about with many ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and perſecutions, God will take notice of our patience and other our graces, though compaſſed about with many infirmities; the Lord will take notice of a little of his good, in a great deal of our evil: let us then look unto, and long for Chriſt, as our Saviour, as our Advocate, as our Head, as our Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as our great Phyſician, and as the Biſhop of our ſouls; and let us run with patience the race that is ſet before us, and being in likelihood near the end of the race.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subpart">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41807:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Conſolations in the Lord Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HE that hath once ſeen God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, dares un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly look the grimmeſt creature in the face, even death it ſelf under any ſhape; all kinde of fear doth flee before ſuch a ſoul: it is only a Chriſtian that is fear-free.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſting of death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the Law; but thanks be to God, that giveth us the victory, through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>for, though</hi> the wages of ſin be death, <hi>yet,</hi> the gift of God is eternal life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>&amp;c. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay,</hi> Thanks be to God, who alwayes cauſeth us to triumph in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>We ſee Jeſus (who was made a little lower then the Angels, for ſuffering of death) crowned with glory and honour, that he (by the grace of God) ſhould taſte death for every man; for it became him (for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many ſons to glory) to make the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41807:41"/> of their ſalvation perfect through ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</p>
               <p>We ſee Jeſus, who himſelf alſo took part of the ſame, fleſh and blood with us, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is, the devil; and deliver them, who through fear of death, were all their life-time ſubject to bondage.</p>
               <p>We ſee Jeſus Chriſt, who was made like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his brethren, that he might be made a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful high-Priest in things pertaining to God, to work reconciliation for the ſins of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for in that he himſelf hath ſuffered being tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</p>
               <p>Seeing that we have a great high Prieſt (Jeſus the Son of God) who is paſſed into the Heavens, let us hold faſt our profeſsion; for we have not an high Prieſt which cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities, but was in all points tempted like as we are, <hi>ſin only excepted: let us therefore come boldly to the throne of grace, that we may obtain mercy, and finde grace in time of need.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:41807:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seeing we are taught by faith, That whatſoever we have need of, and is wanting in us, the ſame is laid up with God for us in Chriſt; it remaineth then, that we do ſeek it of him, and (be, it in ſickneſs or in health) by daily prayer beg it of him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Reading of Scripture, or part of Chapters.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PSalms</hi> 62, 77, 96.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. from v. 1. to v. 29.</p>
               <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1, 5. and the laſt, or part of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> A Prayer where friends are to joyn.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt gracious, moſt glorious Lord God, we thy poor unworthy ſervants are here proſtrate before thy heavenly Majeſty, begging pardon at thy compaſſionate hands, for all the evils that we ſtand guilty of. Oh look upon us, not as we are miſerable ſinners, but as we are by
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41807:42"/> the precious blood of thy dear Son reconciled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, for his ſake we beſeech thee to hear us, and to accept of our prayers; not only for our ſelves, but on the behalf of this thy diſtreſſed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, our Chriſtian brother, whom thou haſt here brought low upon the bed of ſickneſs: we are taught, O Lord, that ſickneſs is brought upon the world for ſin, and that it is inflicted upon thine own people for a tryal and for a bleſſing, that being by thee ſo fatherly chaſtiſed, they may return unto thee (like obedient children) by unfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, holy believing, and humble ſupplication, and not (as with the wicked) for hardning of their hearts. O Lord, we beſeech thee, in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, give to this thy ſick ſervant, grace and ſpiritual ſtrength to ſearch into his own heart, ſo as to finde out, to bewail and to deteſt all his former ſinful actions, freely to forgive eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry injury done unto him, duly to make reſtitution whereſoever there is cauſe, ſo as to be in charity with all men, and to have a clear conſcience void of all offence: Give him of thy grace, O Lord, that he may not take this ſickneſs, or any other thy viſitation, either inſenſibly or impatiently; let him be truly humbled under thy mighty hand, and yet confidently truſt, and conſtantly depend upon thy rich mercy in Chriſt Jeſus, ſo that nothing may be able to ſeparate him from thee, who art his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtay and portion, yea, the only comfort of his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41807:42"/> precious ſoul. And then, good Lord, ſend thy holy Spirit into his heart, to ſupport and ſanctifie him against all his natural weakneſſes, paſſions and infirmities; let thy Almighty power and goodneſs preſerve him againſt all outward cares and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; let thy heavenly Grace, O moſt bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, by thy all-ſufficient merits, purchaſe for him his needful pardon, and let thy moſt precious blood be to him a happy Medicine to all his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies, and a ſoveraign help againſt all his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemies. O grant unto him this bleſſing, that he may quietly repoſe himſelf at this time under the ſhadow of thy wings, void of all fear, and free from all ſpiritual darkneſs, dangers and deſpair. Lord, give him a watchful heart, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly diſpoſed, and thorowly enabled to abandon all tranſitory things here below, and to depart hence with joy, and in the peace of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Good Lord, teach him &amp; enable him upon this his ſick bed, openly, earneſtly, faithfully, unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, and inceſſantly to be confeſſing his ſins, and craving pardon of all his iniquities. O be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed, to keep under Satan, that he may have no power to draw him from ſubmitting to thy divine will and pleaſure: reſtore in him the image of thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt, that ſo long as thou ſhalt afford him any breath, he may live in thy fear, truſt in thy mercy, rely on thy promiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in thy Word, die in thy favour, reſt in thy
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41807:43"/> peace, riſe in thy power, and remain in thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Theſe bleſſings, and what other, mercies this thy ſick creature, or we thy poor ſervants do ſtand in need of, we do humbly and faithfully implore at thy gracious hands, and in the Name, and for the ſake of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; and do conclude all our petitions as he hath taught us; to whom with thee and the holy Spirit, be all glory, power and dominion, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Meditations on the dayes of Death and of Doom.</head>
               <p>DEath was to us (by reaſon of ſin) a dungeon for reſerving the guilty body againſt the day of Judgement; but now, by and through the merits of Chriſt our bleſſed Saviour, death is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, as it were, a perſumed bed for the Elect againſt the day of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Then, O my Lord and Saviour, why ſhould it moleſt or trouble me at all to tread in thy ſteps towards glory? The worſt piece of the horror of death is the grave; that part which is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41807:43"/> feels it not; &amp; the other which is free from corruption, feels an abundant recompence, &amp; foreſees a joyful repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The day of Death, and the day of Doom, are the two Pole-Stars in which we (that are Pilgrims and ſtrangers on earth) muſt at all times be fixing of our eyes: <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> did make his ſepulchre in his garden; <hi>Egyptians</hi> had the picture of death alwayes in their Banquetting-houſes; even ſo ſhould we, in the midſt of our worldly pleaſures, be continually preparing our ſelves, and caſting up our accounts, and daily num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring our dayes.</p>
               <p>Death to the righteous is ever wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; and for the day of Doom, the very name of it, to the godly, is as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; the mentioning of it, is as the ſweeteſt melody; and the thoughts of it, to every good Chriſtian, is as a year of Jubile. Be pleaſed then, Oh heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, to lift up my head and my heart in that great and glorious day; Lord, turn from me thoſe judgements
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41807:44"/> that attend the wicked, and crown me with thoſe myriades of bleſſings which do alwayes accompany thine Elect; and ſo in mercy, come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</p>
               <p>In that great day, we ſhall ſee and meet the ancient Patriarks, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> and the old Prophets, <hi>Elias, Jeremiah, Daniel, Hoſea:</hi> we ſhall alſo behold the four and twenty Elders, the holy Apoſtles, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Mark, James</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> and all the holy Martyrs, <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Stephen,</hi> &amp;c. likewiſe all thoſe harmleſs Infants that were ſlain by <hi>Herod,</hi> who (with their Olive-branches in their hands) do continually ſing, <hi>Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain,</hi> to receive power, and riches, and wiſdom, and ſtrength, and honour, and glory, and bleſſing, both now, and for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subpart">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:41807:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Short Prayers upon any releaſe of Pain.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed and praiſed be thy great and glorious Name, O holy Father in Jeſus Chriſt, for that thou doſt lay no more upon me, nor puniſheſt me to my confuſion: O grant me ſtill a believing heart, and a patient minde, that I may ſtill love thee, and wholly depend upon thee, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly bear all thy fatherly corrections, as it becometh thy faithful ſervant, and a true ſouldier of Jeſus Chriſt. All is thine, and thou art all; to thee only do I flie for relief and ſuccour, knowing that there is no ſtrength nor ſupport but only in thee. Thou wilt not break a bruiſed reed; thou wilt not quench the ſmoaking flax: O thou that delighteſt not in the death of a ſinner, receive me, releaſe my ſoul out of trouble, for thy great Name ſake: let the ſhadow of thy wings be my cover; let the holy Ghoſt be my company; let thy power be my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, my rock and my defence, againſt all fear and danger whatſoever; and do thou in thine infinite goodneſs and mercy, ſay at this time to my poor weak ſoul, <hi>Be of good cheer, I am thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, it is thou alone that haſt ſent me this ſickneſs, be thou pleaſed to come thy ſelf with it, and teach me and enable me to make that ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied uſe thereof, as becometh thy faithful ſervant.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:41807:45"/>
               <p>O Lord, let thy Word be my rule, thy Glory my aim, thy Spirit my guide, thy Angels my guard, thy Promiſes my ſupport, thy People my ſociety, thy Ordinances my delight; then ſhall I be happy, both now and for ever.</p>
               <p>Grant, O Lord God of Heaven and earth, that thy holy Angels may pitch their tents round about me in this my low eſtate, to defend me againſt that evil one; and in thine own appointed time, to convey my ſoul to everlaſting glory.</p>
               <p>When thou, O Lord, ſhalt be finiſhing my weak and evil dayes of ſin, be pleaſed to quiet my tender conſcience, to pardon my many manifold offences, to ſave my precious ſoul, to receive both my body and my ſoul into thy heavenly Kingdom; ſo that I may follow the Lamb whereſoever he goeth.</p>
               <p>Oh, thou that art the Captain of my ſalvation: Oh ſweet Jeſus, that wert made perfect by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, look graciouſly upon thy poor creature, and ſanctifie unto me all the pains of body, and all the troubles of mind which thou ſhalt permit to fall upon me, that I may paſs thorow them to everlaſting happineſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subpart">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:41807:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Conſolations against Pain and fear in Dying.</head>
               <p>THere is pain in the curing of a wound; do we therefore ſuffer it to gangrene, and let it alone to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a limb, perhaps of life? No, we are willing to launce and to heal: ſo let us here ſubmit the body, that the ſoul may be ſafe.</p>
               <p>There be few perſons, but have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured as great, perhaps greater, and for a longer time in their life, then they have at their death.</p>
               <p>We do make the paſſage much the more tedious and difficult, by our bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the thought of death a troubled and an unprepared minde, and in the mean time, forget that Chriſt by his death hath taken away the ſting of death.</p>
               <p>Be not diſmayed: death indeed is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, when it is inflicted by the Law; but it is eaſie, being impoſed by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41807:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> The curſe is now taken off: we are not now under the Law, but under Grace: God, who bleſſed us in life, will not forſake us, he will not neglect us in death; for precious in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of all his Saints.</p>
               <p>Againſt all the apprehenſions and thoughts of death, let this of the holy Spirit be our ſure conſolation: Thanks be to God, that as death is ſwallowed up in victory, ſo he hath given us the victory, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, bleſſed for ever.</p>
               <p>We have the Spirit of Chriſt within us, which will ſecure us, ſearch us, and refreſh us, even all the time of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; yea, it will abide with us for the aſſured comfort of our ſouls.</p>
               <p>We do ſee many men and women to depart out of this life, without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of pain or trouble at all; nay, it is ſometimes with much tranquillity, extraordinary cheerfulneſs, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual joy: let not us then create fear to our ſelves, and expect pain; but with
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41807:46"/> patience, and Chriſtian faith and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, wait upon the Lord for a happy iſſue.</p>
               <p>The body may, and ſometimes doth, ſeem to be in grievous pangs, when as the party feels no pain almoſt at all, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be the Cramp, or the like, while the ſoul in the mean time is in a ſweet repoſe, and preparing it ſelf to come im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to the preſence and bleſſed enjoyment of his dear Lord and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Redeemer; praying ſtill with ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency of ſpirit, Come Lord Jeſus, come and receive my ſoul.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Ejaculations to Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt.</head>
               <p>O Heavenly Father, who ſcourgeſt every ſon whom thou doſt receive, help me thy poor creature, that I may not be weary of thy corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; but be pleaſed to give me ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſubmitting my ſelf to thee, who art the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſpirits, that this chaſtiſement of thine may be ſo much for my preſent and future pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and advantage, that I may be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of thy holineſs.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:41807:47"/>
               <p>Oh holy Jeſus, Son of the everliving God; I have (I do moſt humbly confeſs it) by my many and grievous offences, crucified thee afreſh: but thou (O bleſſed Lord) who didſt pray for thy perſecutors, Oh be pleaſed to intercede alſo for me; and ſuffer not (Oh bleſſed Redeemer) ſuffer not my poor ſoul (the price of thy moſt precious blood) to periſh.</p>
               <p>Oh bleſſed Spirit of Grace, I have by my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold impieties done deſpight unto thee: yet, Oh holy Comforter, though I have often grieved thee, be thou pleaſed to relieve, and ſuccour, and ſanctifie me, and (in this my weakneſs) ſay to my poor ſoul, <hi>I am thy ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We may pray unto the whole Trinity, but more properly unto the firſt perſon, God the Father, in the name of God the Son, and by the aſſiſtance of God the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:41807:47"/>
            <head>PART IV. Meditations upon certain ſignes of Death.</head>
            <div n="1" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Several ſhort Prayers upon any intermiſsion of Pain.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, thou art my God, early will I ſeek thee; my ſoul doth thirſt for thee, my fleſh alſo longeth after thee: I have looked for thee in holineſs, that I might behold thee in power and glory, for thy loving kindneſs is better then life it ſelf: becauſe thou haſt been my helper, therefore under the ſhadow of thy wings will I rejoyce.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, I finde this life to be but a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Pilgrimage, few in days, but full of evil; I am weary of it by reaſon of my ſins: It is enough, O Lord, that I have lived ſo long in this vale of miſery; take my ſoul, O Lord, into thy gracious hands, for I am no better then my Fathers.</p>
               <p>The Law in my members hath ever been war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the Law of my minde, and bringing me into captivity to the Law of ſin: O who ſhall now deliver me from the body of this death! Thou, O Lord, haſt redeemed me with thy moſt precious blood; all praiſe, therefore, and thanks be unto thee, who haſt given me the victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:41807:48"/>
               <p>My ſins, O Lord, have been ſuch as to deſerve eternal death and deſtruction; though I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore too much doted on them, I do now deſire to abhor and to loath the remembrance of them all, and to delight and to depend wholly on thy mercy. O bleſſed Lamb of God, that takeſt away the ſins of the world, have mercy upon me: O ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world, receive my ſpirit; thou haſt redeemed it, O Lord, thou God of truth.</p>
               <p>O Lord, the devil is ever buſie in taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage againſt our poor ſouls; but moſt of all, when we are most weak and moſt unable to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with him: Be pleaſed (good Lord) in this my weakneſs to rebuke Satan, and let thy holy Spirit comfort my diſtreſſed ſoul, with aſſurance of thy love in Chriſt Jeſus: aſſwage my pain; O Lord, increaſe my faith and my patience, and in thine own good time, give a happy end to theſe my troubles.</p>
               <p>O Lord, for thy mercies ſake give me full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that whatſoever in this my weakneſs and ſickneſs thou ſhalt pleaſe to lay upon me, it ſhall come from a bleſſed Father, a faithful Creator, and a bleſſed Redeemer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subpart">
               <head>II. A Prayer to be uſed by my Friends.</head>
               <p>OH moſt bleſſed Lord God, we are proſtrating our ſelves before thy heavenly Majeſty, in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41807:48"/> the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, on the behalf of this thy ſick ſervant; thou only knoweſt what is fitteſt for him, health or ſickneſs, life or death: Good Lord, ſanctifie this thy viſitation to him, that by it he may be more &amp; more humble in the ſight of his ſins, &amp; ſo be longing after Chriſt. Oh, enlighten his minde, that he may know the hope of his calling, and what is the exceeding riches of thy mercy in Chriſt Jeſus toward all that believe in thee; and ſo ſtrengthen his faith, that he may lay faſt hold on the merits of our bleſſed Saviour: Lord, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect him from the malice of Satan, allay the edge of his aſſaults, that they may never make him to deſpair of thy compaſſion to him in this his low eſtate: Remove from him a dull ſpirit, with all manner of ſecure and hardned thoughts, and all wordly deſires and creature-comforts. Lord, give him patience, with Chriſtian courage and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, to bear whatſoever thou ſhalt pleaſe to lay upon him: Oh, vouchſafe unto him comfort in his conſcience, joy in the Spirit, and peace in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving; together with a ſetled and a well-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded expectation of eternal life and ſalvation, through thine infinite love in Chriſt Jeſus: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute not unto him his own unrighteouſneſs, but the righteouſneſs of thy dear Son, ſo as thy poor weak ſervant may appear righteous in thy ſight. Lord, raiſe him up unto thy ſelf, with thoſe heavenly ſighs and groans which are not to be expreſſed:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41807:49"/> Oh, keep and ſave his ſoul; command thy holy Angels to be about him, for his everlaſting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and chaſe far away from him all evil and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant ſpirits, that they annoy him not in this time of his diſtreſs: let him more and more abandon the world, and even long to be looſed, ſo as to be with Chriſt. Oh, cauſe his laſt hour to be his joyfulleſt hour, his laſt words to be his beſt words, and his laſt thoughts to be his heavenlieſt thoughts. And, good Lord, we beſeech thee, put thy word of Grace and godly Wiſdom into our hearts and tongues, ſo as upon all occaſions to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy minde holily, ſoundly and cheerfully, to the comfort, and to the refreſhing of his precious and immortal ſoul. And now, thou good and gracious God, be pleaſed to teach us in him, and in this houſe of mourning, to conſider our own end, and ſo to lay it to heart, that we being now in health, may yet be labouring and preparing for our diſſolution, and for a holy, a joyful, and a comfortable leaving of this life, this valley of tears. Lord, hear us for this thy poor ſick ſervant, and hear us for our ſelves: but above all, hear us for the ſake of thy dearly beloved Son Jeſus Chriſt; to whom, with thy heavenly and bleſſed Spirit, be given all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and praiſe, power and glory, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subpart">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:41807:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Queſtions with Anſwers, upon any ſigne of Dying.</head>
               <p>DOſt thou believe, That Almighty God, the Trinity of perſons in unity of Eſſence, hath by his power made Heaven and Earth, and all that is therein; and that by his divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he doth ſtill govern the ſame, ſo that nothing comes in the world, nor to thy ſelf, but what his holy arm and counſel had fore-ordained to be done?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All this I do believe: Lord, help my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doſt thou really confeſs, That thou haſt tranſgreſſed and broken the holy Commandments of God, in thought, word, and deed; and that (for the ſame) thou haſt deſerved the wrath of God, even all the miſeries of this life and hereafter, even everlaſting torments in Hell, if God ſhould deal with thee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy deſerts?</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:41807:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>All this I do acknowledge: Lord Jeſu, pardon my tranſgreſsions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Art thou not ſorry in thine heart, that thou haſt ſo broken his Laws, and ſo much neglected his ſervice, and ſo hotly purſued the world, and ſo eagerly doat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon thy vain pleaſures; and wouldſt thou not now lead a holier life, if thou wert to begin thy dayes again?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt I am heartily ſorry for my miſdoings, and fain I would with more conſtancy have ſerved thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doſt thou not from thy heart deſire to be reconciled to God in Jeſus Chriſt, thy only Mediator, who is at the right hand of God, and now appearing for thee, and making interceſſion at the throne of grace for thy ſorrowful ſoul?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh, it is reconciliation to God in Chriſt, that I above all things do moſt humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doſt thou renounce all confidence in all other Mediators, Saints or Angels, believing that Jeſus Chriſt alone is the Mediator of the New Teſtament, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41807:50"/> able to ſave all ſuch as come to God by him? And, canſt thou with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>David,</hi> ſay to Chriſt, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? there is none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is none but Chriſt, my ſoul ſhall ever ſing; there is none but Chriſt that can inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede for the ſins of the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Portions of Scripture to be read.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PSal.</hi> 103. or ſome part of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> 3. or ſome part of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. or ſome part of them.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. or ſome part of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> More Queſtions with Anſwers, upon any ſigne of Dying.</head>
               <p>DOſt thou confidenly believe, and aſſuredly hope to be ſaved by the only merit of the bitter death and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Jeſus Chriſt, not placing the thought of ſalvation in thine own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, nor in any other means or crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41807:51"/> whatſoever, being certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that there is no ſalvation in any other, nor any other name under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by which thou canſt be ſaved?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jeſus is the only Saviour of the world; therefore let all creatures bow down before him, and bleſs his holy Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doſt thou from thy heart forgive all injuries and offences done unto thee by any perſon whatſoever? And doſt thou as freely from thy heart ask forgiveneſs of all whom thou haſt any way wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in thought, word or deed? Doſt thou caſt out of thy heart all rancour and malice againſt any perſon, ſo as to appear before the face of Jeſus Chriſt (the Prince of peace) in perfect love and charity?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do humbly pray for ſuch true charity as to forgive all, and I do from my heart ask for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth thy conſcience accuſe thee of any thing that thou haſt unjuſtly taken, ſtill with-holding the ſame, for which, without reſtitution, there can be no true
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41807:51"/> repentance, and without ſuch repentance there can be no ſalvation; nor ſhalt thou be able to look Chriſt in the face, when thou ſhalt appear before his judgement-ſeat?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have been willing to ſatisfie all whom I have wronged: but alas, who is able to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber all his errors!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doſt thou firmly believe, That thy body ſhall be raiſed out of the grave at the ſound of the laſt trumpet, and that both thy body and thy ſoul ſhall be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together again in the Reſurrection-day, to appear before the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thence to go with him into the Kingdom of Heaven, there to live in everlaſting bliſs and glory?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My faith, alas, is weak; but thy grace, O Lord, is ſufficient for me: O Lord, let thy holy Spirit aſsiſt me, and lead me into the way of everlaſting glory.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subpart">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:41807:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Short Prayers upon any leſſening of Pain.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt bleſſed Saviour, be pleaſed to place thy precious Paſſion, thy Croſs, and thy Death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween my ſoul &amp; thy diſpleaſure; and let the merits of thy obedience ſtand between thy heavenly Fathers juſtice and my diſobedience; and from theſe bodily pains, receive my ſoul into thine everlaſting peace: and good Lord, give ear unto this my cry: <hi>O Jeſu, receive my ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord Jeſus Chriſt, forſake not him, that in great diſtreſs doth flie to thee for ſuccour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief: O ſound that ſweet and comfortable voice into my fainting ſoul, which thou wert pleaſed to utter to the penitent Thief; <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, I know and do believe, that whoſoever liveth and truſteth in thee, who art the reſurrection and the life, ſhall never die: Oh then, vouchſafe favour to thy poor creature, that I may hear that bleſſed voice of thine, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O most gracious God, whoſe nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41807:52"/> is ever to have mercy and to forgive, receive my humble ſupplications; and though I be ſo much bound with the chains of my ſins, yet Lord, let the pitifulneſs of thy great mercy looſe me, and ſet me at liberty, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saviour and Redeemer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O holy Lord, fit and prepare me for my laſt conflict; and by the ſupport of thy bleſſed Spirit, and the aſſiſtance of thy heavenly Angels, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to aſſiſt and ſtrengthen me againſt the aſſaults of Satan, that notwithſtanding his mortal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, I may ſtill hold me faſt, and keep my ſelf cloſe to thee in all holy believing, ſo as humbly and ſtedfaſtly to reſolve, that though thou ſhouldſt ſlay me, yet to put my truſt in thee, and to place my whole confidence in thine everlaſting mercies in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> When weakneſs and faintneſs increaſe, let friends help, with theſe ſhort ejaculations.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, bear me thy poor ſick ſervant in thy gracious arms, to the land of the living.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord, bring me, I beſeech thee, by thy power and goodneſs, to thy holy habitation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Plant me, O Lord, in the mountain of thine
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41807:53"/> inheritance, the place which thou haſt prepared to dwell in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord, make me to be one of the joyful Citizens of thy holy Jeruſalem, which is above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh Lord, as my weakneſs ſhall encreaſe, ſo let my patience, the hope of thy favour, and aſſurance of thy mercy in Chriſt Jeſus, ſtill increaſe more and more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh Lord, let thy grace and bleſſing be upon me, that I may ſafely paſs thorow this vale of miſery, and finiſh my courſe with joy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, lift up the light of thy countenance upon me, and grant me peace in the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh holy Father, if it be thy bleſſed will, give an end to my labours, and releaſe me of my pains.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subpart">
               <head>VIII. More of Ejaculations when faintneſs increaſeth.</head>
               <p>SWeet Jeſu, receive my ſoul; ſweet Jeſu, receive my ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come, Lord Jeſu, come, for thy ſervant cometh: I am willing, Lord, help my weakneſs.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:41807:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, let thy holy Angels ſtand round about my bed, and guard me from that evil one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, lay not my ſins to my charge, but look upon him that maketh the atonement; <hi>Thy Chriſt, my Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, to thee belongeth mercy and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; have pity on my ſoul, and pardon my ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, ſay, to my ſouls everlaſting joy and comfort, <hi>I am thy ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lamb of God, that takeſt away the ſins of the world, have mercy upon me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, make clean my heart within me, and take not thy holy Spirit from me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I do commend my ſpirit into thy hands: thou haſt redeemed me, O God, thou God of mercy, of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subpart">
               <head>IX. A Prayer by friends, at leaving this Life.</head>
               <p>OH moſt gracious Lord God, and loving Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Jeſus Chriſt, who art our portion, our ſtrong refuge, a ſure defence, and a very preſent
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41807:54"/> help in time of trouble: Oh, lift up thy merciful countenance at this inſtant upon thy weak ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, who now is coming to appear in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: Oh, thou which art the great preſerver of men, take pity and compaſſion upon him, waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all his natural and ſinful pollutions, by the all-ſufficient merits of Chriſt Jeſus his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood, that they may never be laid to his charge, nor hinder his happy paſſage to everlaſting bleſſedneſs. O Lord, increaſe his faith, preſerve his ſoul from the malice and danger of the devil, and all his evil angels; comfort him with thy holy Spirit, cauſe him now to feel and finde, that thou art his gracious Father, and thou art reconciled unto him in thy dearly beloved: ſave him, O Lord; O Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſave the price of thine own blood, and ſuffer not him to be loſt, whom thou haſt ſo dearly purchaſed. Oh, receive his poor ſoul (as thou didſt the penitent thief) into thy heavenly Paradiſe; let thy bleſſed Angels conduct him thither, as they carried the ſoul of thy beloved <hi>Lazarus;</hi> and vouchſafe unto him a joyful reſurrection at the great and laſt day. O holy Father in Jeſus Chriſt, hear us for him, who cannot now ſpeak for himſelf; and hear thy dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloved Son, our only Mediator, both for him and for us all: It is in his Name, and for his ſake, that we ſeek unto thee in the behalf of the precious ſoul of this thy weak ſervant: to him,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41807:54"/> with thy bleſſed ſelf and holy Spirit, we do render all ſervice, honour and praiſe, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subpart">
               <head>X. Another Prayer at yielding up the Ghoſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt gracious, and moſt merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Jeſus Chriſt, be pleaſed to caſt a compaſſionate eye upon the immortal ſoul of this thy languiſhing creature; Lord, hear our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for him, and thy Chriſt, our bleſſed Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, for us all: the ſnares of death do encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs him, he is ſore bruiſed, and broken, and brought very low; the pangs that are upon him are unſpeakable. O Lord, pour the oyl of gladneſs into his fainting ſoul: aſſure him, that thou haſt caſt all his ſins behinde thy back, and that there is a ſweet peace wrought between him and thee, by him who is the Prince of peace. Oh, give him that inward joy, and ſuch comfortable taſte of eternal happineſs, that he may rejoyce in thee, and forget his preſent anguiſh, and patiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the ſame, for that endleſs joy that is ſet before him: and though theſe faint, and theſe conſuming fits have now deprived him of ſpeech, yet, good Lord, let the Comforter, that is, the bleſſed Spirit, within him, make requeſts for him, with prevailing ſighs and groans that cannot be expreſſed; ever crying out, <hi>Lord Jeſu, receive
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41807:55"/> my ſoul, Lord Jeſu, receive my ſpirit;</hi> ſo let death be to him none other then a joyful meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſent from thee, the father of all conſolation, to call and convey him from this valley of tears, to everlaſting bliſs: And, let the bleſſed and glorious Name of <hi>JESUS,</hi> be ſtill the chief and the only anchor of his precious ſoul, the ſole foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his faith, and the ſacred ſtaff and ſure ſupporter, even to the laſt gaſp. Hear us, O Lord, O thou that art the preſerver of men, hear us for this thy poor ſervant, and have mercy upon him, and embrace him in thine own moſt gracious arms, and all for thy dearly beloved Son Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, that he may now come and be with thee for ever, to ſing with thy holy Saints and bleſſed Angels, <hi>Bleſſing, Honour, Glory and Power be unto him that ſitteth on the Throne, and unto the Lamb, for ever and ever.</hi> Hallelujah. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:41807:55"/>
            <head>PART V. Being ten bleſſed Examples of holy Perſons, relating to a happy paſſage out of this Life to a better.</head>
            <div n="1" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>I. Philippus Lodovicus,</hi> Earle of <hi>Hanaw, Reinek,</hi> &amp;c. a German Prince. He ſtickned, <hi>July 29. 1612.</hi> and departed this life upon Sunday the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> being not long after his return as Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador out of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JUly</hi> 29. 1612. His Excellency, as his cuſtom was, went in his Coach to the Woods, with ſome of his Council and Court-ſervants: feeling himſelf ſomewhat ill in the heat, he did take ſome reſt in the fields.</p>
               <p>The next day, he went to the weekly Sermon, and the publick Prayers at the Church in the old City; but at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, he found himſelf worſe, and went to take ſome reſt upon his bed.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:41807:56"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 2. Sunday, he was let blood, and did take ſome Phyſick, and was ſo well upon it, as to riſe and viſit his Lady, who was then in childe-bed. After that, he called to one of his Counſellors, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him about ſerious matters, and chiefly concerning the Church of <hi>Hanaw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. He was ill again, ſo as he began to prepare for a Chriſtianly departure out of this life: he called for his Lady and children; in their preſence and hearing he gave an account of his faith, and that with ſingular zeal, and holy courage.</p>
               <p>His Lady and children being retired, he conferred with his Council, upon what did concern the Church, the School, the Country, and the Subjects; and then took his leave of them, in a moſt friendly and Chriſtianly manner.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Came divers Courtiers upon his requeſt, and after ſome diſcourſe, with tears he parted with them, they taking their dear Lord by the hand. Then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:41807:56"/> of the Citizens came and had very comfortable words from him; after which, they with much ſadneſs took their leaves of him. Laſtly, the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, both of the old and of the new City being called for, he told them, that his deſire was once more before his end, (with his Houſhold) to receive the holy Supper of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring withal, that this was not groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon any ſuperſtition, or that, <hi>Ex opere operato,</hi> it is meritorious, but that it is chiefly for the ſtrengthening of his weak faith, and for the teſtifying of his profeſſion, yet once again, before God and the world: and this did the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters accordingly perform.</p>
               <p>This night he could not ſleep almoſt at all; ſo he cauſed ſeveral Pſalms to be ſung, and ſometimes he ſang himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 5. He called for his Will; and after ſome alteration, he did deliver it to his Chamberlain, with charge to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it in due time to his Council.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Came to him his Lady-ſiſter, the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41807:57"/> Lady <hi>Emilia</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> from <hi>Heydelberg,</hi> whom he cheerfully received, with theſe words; <hi>Madam, many of my friends have ſtood weeping about my bed, but none could break my heart, and provoke my tears, but your Ladiſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Divers of his ſervants coming from the monthly Sermon, he did call to hear from every one of them, ſome good Doctrine that they had heard.</p>
               <p>He had a very ill night, and was ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to have ſome of the penitential Pſalms to be ſung, he ſometimes bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a part. After that, ſome of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines did mention to him thoſe places of Scripture, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. &amp; <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. to which he gave ſweet and ſpiritual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, and ſaid, <hi>Oh, now do I finde and feel the free remiſsion of all my ſins, that I am a childe of God, and an heir of eternal life; yea, I do feel the vertue of my Saviour Chriſts blood refreſhing of my ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lady <hi>Emilia</hi> being now come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to him, he ſaid, <hi>Ah, my loving and vertuous Lady, I am a ſick man; rehearſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41807:57"/> to me, I pray, ſome comfortable ſentence out of the Scripture.</hi> She ſaid, <hi>She was a poor weak creature; but ſhe did ſee, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God (bleſſed be his Name) did greatly comfort him.</hi> He ſtill urging it, ſhe did recite that place, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world,</hi> &amp;c. At which he cheerfully uttered theſe words; <hi>Well ſaid, my noble Siſter: This is the greateſt and the ſureſt comfort of all Gods faithful people; with this comfort will I die happily: I beſeech and pray from my heart, to my gracious God, for ſuch a bleſſed departure, through the vertue of the ſatisfaction of my Lord Jeſus Chriſt. O my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Christ, into thy hands I commit my ſoul, both now and for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, his Excellency cauſed ſome of his little Prayer-books to be brought to his bed, and appointed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of his children, one, writing therein their ſeveral names, and adding thereunto his Chriſtianly and Fatherly admonition.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:41807:58"/>
               <p>For his eldeſt Son, <hi>Philippus Mauritius,</hi> upon his <hi>German Bible,</hi> he did write thus:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>MY Son, <hi>Philippus Mauritius,</hi> Count of <hi>Hanaw,</hi> Fear God, and keep his holy Commandments: I have been this night ſore troubled, and in great anguiſh; I have thought on many things, which I wiſh, my Childe, that you could know; yet, thus much I tell you, Keep thy ſelf, even all thy life-time, cloſe unto thy God; his gracious help, and his bleſſed aſsiſtance, will be evermore moſt neceſſary for thee: I would to God, that I could write the great riches of his infinite mercy, goodneſs, and faithfulneſs, that have been experimented by me this long time: I bleſs the Lord, I have already the foretaſte of everlaſting glory; <hi>Therefore will I ſing unto the Lord as long as I live,</hi> Pſa. <hi>104.33. I will ſing praiſe to my God, while I have my being: my Meditation of him ſhall be ſweet; I will be glad in the Lord.</hi> The Lord help thee unto me in due
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41807:58"/> time. <hi>Amen.</hi> In theſe pangs of death, I do deſire to be delivered, and to be with my Lord Jeſus Chriſt: O Lord Jeſus Christ, thou faithful Saviour, how do I love thee! Thy promiſes are true, thy love is great, thy heart is faithful towards me: I do commend my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into thy hands, thou dear and faithful God: Thou haſt moſt graciouſly delivered and ſanctified me; Lord, I do wait on thy ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Thy faithful Father,</hi> Philippus Lodovicus,</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond Son, <hi>Willielmus Reynhart,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his Book with theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>MY dear Son, ſerve thy God with thy whole heart, in Sprit and in Truth; I have deſtinated thee thereunto: eſteem it not to be any ſhame unto thee, to ſerve God and his Church; for God is the greateſt God, he is thy Creator; keep in honour the true ſervice of God. Obey and ſerve thy dear Mother, under whoſe heart thou haſt lain; honour and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41807:59"/> ſerve thy eldeſt Brother, as thy Lord, for ſuch is the Ordinance, and my will alſo: bear with him if thou be in the right, for thou art then more happy then he; but if thou doſt not walk uprightly in thy words, then art not thou happy. Love thy Brothers and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters from the heart; love thy Houſe; do good to the Poor, according to thy ability, then ſhall the Lord bleſs thee. Beware of drunkenneſs, of diſſoluteneſs and all unclean ſpeeches, as thou wouldſt do of fire: Honour thy State; be industrious in all things; read and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and that continually, the <hi>119</hi> Pſalm; let thine Aſtrologians be the <hi>28</hi> of <hi>Deute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronomy.</hi> So I commit thee to God.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Thy faithful Father unto death,</hi> Philippus Lodovicus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The eldeſt Daughter, <hi>Lady Charlette Loiſa,</hi> received her Book, with theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>FEar, honour, and love thy God from thy heart; have his Commandments conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually before thine eyes, take thy whole delight
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41807:59"/> therein: Honour, with all filial obedience, thy loving Mother; keep thy mouth cloſe with a lock; eſteem honeſty and modeſty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the goods and treaſures of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world: God bleſs thee, my loving Childe.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Thy loving Father unto death,</hi> Philippus Lodovicus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The ſecond Daughter, Lady <hi>Emilia Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabetha,</hi> received her Book from him, with theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>HAve God always before thine eyes: Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy Mother with obedience and with love; keep honeſty and modeſty, for theſe will be thy beſt riches, and thy chiefeſt jewel.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Thy faithful Father unto death,</hi> Philippus Lodovicus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:41807:60"/>
               <p>The youngeſt Daughter, Lady <hi>Catherina Juliana,</hi> received her Book with theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>DEar Childe, be vertuous: Have thy Creator alwayes before thine eyes; fear thy God, even all the days of thy life; love and honour thy bleſſed Saviour, who did ſhed his moſt precious blood for thee: break off from thine evil will betimes; be humble and obedient. Humility, honeſty and ſilence, do more adorn a Lady, then either pearls or other coſtly jewels.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Thy faithful Father unto death,</hi> Philippus Lodovicus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Theſe Prayer-books being thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, his Excellency cauſed alſo the late-born Lord to be brought before the bed; ſighed ſadly over him, touched him with his hand, and prayed, that the Lord would alſo bleſs that tender Infant with his grace.</p>
               <p>Lying down again, his bed being new
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41807:60"/> made, he (ſtretching out both his arms) ſaid to one of his Counſellors, <hi>Ecce di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum miraculum, hominem jam mortuum, viribus tamen adhuc integrum:</hi> That is, <hi>Loe a divine miracle; a man already dead, and yet having his full ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this (his underſtanding remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very good) he cauſed divers things to be read out of a little Song-book, and then took it to him, and writ in it, <hi>This Song have I uſed many years;</hi> and then commanded it to be laid upon his heart, as ſoon as he ſhould be departed.</p>
               <p>A while after, he called before him all the Miniſters, both of the old and of the new City, and alſo ſome of the Country-Miniſters, with whom he did diſcourſe of the true ſaving faith, and of a Chriſtianly departure out of this life; telling them, <hi>That he would not willingly, in this his weakneſs, be without a Preacher by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He did often ſigh and pray from his heart for a mitigation of his pains, and for ſhortning the pangs of death, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41807:61"/> ſo for an underſtanding end; and did uſe many comfortable ſpeeches, to the joy and admiration of ſuch as were his aſſiſtants.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Aug.</hi> Friday, his Excellency feeling the time of death approaching, his heart was full of godly comfort, and of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly conſolation, ſpeaking with ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar zeal, of the miſery of this life, of the death of a Chriſtian, &amp; of eternal ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Then ſaying, <hi>Ah, Sirs, loving Sirs, I have ſeen the glory of God; what do I care for this world! I have kiſſed the hem of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Lord Jeſus Chriſt; I am now climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the ladder of</hi> Jacob <hi>up to heaven, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward my God and Saviour.</hi> And while he was full of theſe expreſſions, and caſt his arms from him, he ſaid, <hi>All things here below, do now ſtink before me: Tell this to my children, chiefly to my Steward, that he nor they ſeek too much after worldly things, but to put their whole truſt in God. Ah, my dear people,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>how much trouble have you with me, miſerable creature!</hi> Then he called, <hi>Open all the doors, let all my people
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41807:61"/> come in, that they may ſee how joyfully I do die, and ſo be comforted by my example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Phyſicians warning him not to ſpeak too much: <hi>Ah,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Should not I ſpeak of my loving and moſt gracious God? He hath given me, and he continueth to me, a tongue to that end.</hi> Again, when the Phyſicians ſpake againſt opening the windows; <hi>What,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>ſhould not I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the fair Heavens, whither I ſhall come anon?</hi> He did oftentimes lift up his hands and his eyes to heaven, uſing theſe words; <hi>Oh, thou great and strong God, thou Almighty God, thou holy God, thou good and true God:</hi> To which he addeth the ſhort Prayers, which Dr. <hi>Luther</hi> uſed to call <hi>Stoſſgebete.</hi> He did many times repeat theſe ſhort ſentences, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50.15. &amp; 91.15. &amp; 27.14. &amp; 23.1. &amp; 3.8. l— and yet it did appear, that ſoul and body, fleſh &amp; ſpirit, were in conflict. After ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>groanings,</hi> he did keep himſelf quiet a while, ſaying, <hi>One combate is now paſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 8. very early, he ſent for his Lady, and the Lady <hi>Emilia,</hi> from whom
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41807:62"/> they heard many comfortable expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and then, with abundance of tears, and ſad complaints, they took their leaves of him.</p>
               <p>Though he complained much of pain, he never was without comfort, but was often times heard to ſay, <hi>Mors mihi glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſa erit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the night, he was in a very great conflict, and turning from the Miniſter, ſaid, <hi>He could not receive his conſolations, he could not hold them faſt;</hi> whereupon the Miniſter went preſently to the bed, and fell about his neck, and ſpake to him out of that place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.2. which had been his delight; ſo he turned to the Miniſter again, and put his hands into the Miniſters hands: then offering to ſleep, the Miniſter ſaid theſe words; <hi>In the Name of the Lord Jeſus Christ, I do lay my hand upon your head, beſeeching him to ſtrengthen and refreſh you.</hi> So he ſlept; and when he did awake, he called for him again to do the like: which he did, and alſo prayed; ſo he did ſleep again.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:41807:62"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 9. Sunday, the Sermon-bell in the old City ringing, he ſaid, <hi>Never did that Bell ſound ſo ſweet in my ears, as now it doth.</hi> Then he ſaid, <hi>Let us ſing:</hi> and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down his head, he began to ſing the Song of the Angels, out of <hi>Luke</hi> 2.14. the company joyning with him; after that, a part of the 118 <hi>Pſal.</hi> and then the firſt part of the 116 <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After a while, the Miniſter and he prepared for receiving of the bleſſed Sacrament, but firſt he made his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion as he was able; and being long, it was not all at the ſame inſtant.</p>
               <p>The Sacrament being over, and the Miniſter and company preparing for Prayer, he obſerved it, and bad them kneel down and pray; and he did zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly repeat every word, eſpecially the Lords Prayer, and the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith: and as ſome good Chriſtians did uſe any choice and holy ſentence to comfort him, he repeated the ſame after them, ſo long as his tongue could do it.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:41807:63"/>
               <p>The Miniſter concluded with the words before-mentioned, of <hi>John</hi> 3.16. while his Excellency yielded up his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit quietly and bleſſedly. In the mean time, the Miniſter cryed often aloud by him, <hi>O Lord Jeſus Christ, I do commit my ſpirit into thy hands; Thou hast delivered me, O thou moſt true and faithful God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The words of our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. wherewith the Miniſter (as hath been ſaid) did comfort his Excellency at the laſt hour; thoſe words were by himſelf written, as were many other particular remarkable ſentences, in his <hi>Germane Bible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is obſervable, that his Excellency did depart this Life, after the ending of the Sermon in the old Church, and of the Prayer which was there conceived and uſed for the benefit of his ſoul.</p>
               <p>Thus did this pious Proteſtant Prince end his dayes, in much honour and peace, <hi>Aug.</hi> 9. 1612.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subpart">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:41807:63"/>
               <head>II. <hi>John Meautis,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Secretary to the Lord-Keeper <hi>Finch,</hi> departed this Life, <hi>Dec.</hi> 22. 1635. whoſe ſayings on his Death-bed, were ſuch as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Am going to Heaven, and I will come no more to you, as well as I love you:</hi> which was very much; for, there were preſent, his dear wife, ſome of his children, his beloved ſiſter, and others. Again,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come my glory; Come, come, come: Oh, he is come, he is come.</hi> Again,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In your patience poſſeſs your ſouls.</hi> Again,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Make your Election ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being asked by his ſiſter, What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort he found in his ſoul, he ſaid, <hi>I have abundance of comfort, and of aſſurance too, in the ſweet and tender mercies of my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, the Miniſter demanding of him, How he ſtood in charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his neighbour; he cheerfully did anſwer, <hi>I am at peace with all men: I have done wrong to no man ſo neer as I could; I
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:41807:64"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ar no man any grudge, nor any ill will at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo he departed indeed, in peace, bleſſed be the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Wife of Mr. <hi>John Juxon,</hi> a Citizen of <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore her Converſion (which was about the 22 year of her age, and five years before her death) ſhe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſaid, <hi>She did wonder what people meant, to run dagling to hear Sermons;</hi> but afterwards, if ſhe were in <hi>London,</hi> ſhe was at nine or ten Sermons in a week, beſides catechiſing; and ſo, that the Word and the Spirit did work mightily upon her, even voluntarily to confeſs to her Miniſter, how vain her former life had been.</p>
               <p>Then ſhe never miſſed reading the Bible morning and evening, ſo as ſhe read it thorow oftentimes.</p>
               <p>In her health, ſhe uſed to ſet down in writing much of her ſpiritual life, which
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41807:64"/> at her death was found lodged with thoſe things that ſhe eſteemed of moſt value.</p>
               <p>She made conſcience of words, as well as of deeds; of the luſt of the eye, as well as of the act of uncleanneſs; of thoughts, as well as of deeds. She was exact in keeping her times of Prayer in private; wherein ſhe complained of hardneſs of heart, bewailed her failings, and bemoaned the diſtractions that ſhe oftentimes found in her ſelf: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe did many times perſwade with her Husband, not to encumber himſelf with too much worldly imployment.</p>
               <p>She feared both the company, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the doctrine of ſuch Miniſters, as ſeemed to afford her over-much liberty in her courſe of life.</p>
               <p>In the time of her long ſickneſs, ſhe was very ſenſible of the want of hearing Gods Word preached; and reſolved (if God ſhould give her ſo much ſtrength) to go to Church, though carried in a chair.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:41807:65"/>
               <p>In her health, ſhe did often wiſh to be diſſolved, and that ſhe might not live to have her confidence weakned; and rejoyced often, that the Lord had freed her from helliſh fears, and that ſhe found much peace in him; and yet not ſo fully, but that ſometimes ſhe pitifully groaned under the ſence of unbelief: though ſome Miniſters did tell her, that they did never believe aright, that did never doubt.</p>
               <p>She oftentimes gave good rewards in gold, for preaching upon ſubjects that were choſen by her: one was, Of the curſed eſtate of man by nature; and of the uttermoſt terrors of the Law againſt ſin, to break her ſtony heart.</p>
               <p>She loved poor godly Chriſtians, yea, and many times preferred them before her rich kindred.</p>
               <p>It was thought, by thoſe that knew her well, that ſhe did affect holineſs far above ſalvation; and hath ſometimes been ſo raviſhed with it, as heartily to deſire (if it were the will of God) never
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41807:65"/> to go into the world again, but to ſpend her dayes in fellowſhip with God.</p>
               <p>Though ſhe were ſubject to paſſion, yet ſhe was contented to ſit down under any wrong that was done her, as being perſwaded, that God would clear her innocence.</p>
               <p>She gave the Miniſter, which ſhe did apprehend to be the means (under God) of her converſion, no leſs then 50 l.</p>
               <p>After ſhe was converted, ſhe did put out her children no more, but nurſed them with her own breaſts.</p>
               <p>Being demanded by ſome friends, if her conſcience did not teſtifie with her, that in the time of her health ſhe had zealouſly ſought after God, and care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully walked in his wayes; to which ſhe gave this anſwer, That her Chamber and her Cloſet, her Orchard and her Garden, her Turret and her Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, even every corner in the houſe, could teſtifie, that ſhe had alwayes moſt earneſtly ſought after God.</p>
               <p>There was nothing, no not her own
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41807:66"/> children, that did move her to deſire life.</p>
               <p>When death, after above a years ſore ſickneſs and extremity of pain, ſeemed to draw near, ſhe called the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to God in prayer, and as earneſt ſhe was for others to pray with her and for her: and ſo in great aſſurance, and faith and patience, ſhe expired, when ſhe was not full 27 years of age.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Dr. <hi>Uſher,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen he was but 14 years old, he was preparing himſelf for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and (as alwayes afterward) upon the Saturday before, he went to a Brook-ſide, where he did meditate and bewail his ſins.</p>
               <p>His Father's intention was to ſend him from <hi>Ireland</hi> to ſtudy the Law at the Inns of Court here; which being his Fathers pleaſure, he aſſented unto: but his Father dying in 1598. he was at liberty, and devoted himſelf to the ſtudy of Divinity.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:41807:66"/>
               <p>When he was 19 years old, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted with <hi>Fitz Symonds</hi> the Jeſuite, <hi>De Antichriſto,</hi> who afterward knowing more of him, would not call him Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, but <hi>Acatholicorum doctiſsimus;</hi> that is, of ſuch as are not Catholicks, the moſt learned.</p>
               <p>Before he was 21 years of age, he was ordained Miniſter by his Uncle <hi>Henry Uſher,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and Primate of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt Church-preferment he had, was to be Chancellor of <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At 27 years of age, he commenced Batchelor in Divinity; and five years after, Doctor of Divinity.</p>
               <p>He was ſcandalized to King <hi>James,</hi> under the title of a Puritan; but this being (upon the King's diſcourſe with him) cleared, was the occaſion of his preferment to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Meath</hi> there. The <hi>Motto</hi> of his Epiſcopal ſeal, was, <hi>Vae mihi, ſi non Evangelizavero;</hi> which he continued alſo in the Seal of his Primacy.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:41807:67"/>
               <p>In 1624. when he was 44 years of age, he was tranſlated from <hi>Meath,</hi> and made Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being come into <hi>England,</hi> he was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the Wife of the Lord <hi>Mordant</hi> (afterward Earle of <hi>Peterborow</hi>) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her Religion againſt that of her Lords, which was Popiſh; where he prevailed againſt the Popiſh Prieſt that was choſen by the Lord <hi>Mordant,</hi> which drew his Lordſhip to the true Religion; and for which he was ever after, both loved and helped in thoſe times of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by the ſaid Lady: there he lived 9 or 10 years, and there he dyed.</p>
               <p>He did uſe Prayer (beſide that in his Cloſet) four times a day; that is, at ſix in the morning, and eight in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening with his Family, and then before dinner and ſupper in the Chappel.</p>
               <p>By the diſturbances of thoſe times, he was brought very low; and then by Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> was invited to a large maintenance in <hi>France,</hi> with liberty to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41807:67"/> live where he pleaſed with the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants: ſo by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> he was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the place of <hi>Honorius</hi> Profeſſor at <hi>Leyden,</hi> which had an ample ſtipend; but he refuſed both.</p>
               <p>The laſt Sermon he preached, was in 1656. at <hi>Hammerſmith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 20. 1656. he ſickned at the Counteſs of <hi>Peterborows</hi> houſe at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> He firſt, in the evening, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a pain like the Sciatica in his Hip. The next morning, the pain removed, and was much in his ſide: a Phyſician was ſent for, who did what he conceived was fit for him; but it continuing, and his ſpirits decaying, he applied himſelf to Prayer.</p>
               <p>Upon ſome abatement of the torture, he did piouſly adviſe thoſe that were about him, to provide in their health to encounter death, that ſo they might then have nothing elſe to do but to die; of which, after a ſhort time for ſetling of his worldly eſtate, he took great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to finde its approach.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:41807:68"/>
               <p>In Prayer, he had at firſt the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a godly Miniſter there preſent, but afterward he deſired to be left to his own private.</p>
               <p>The laſt words that he was heard to utter, in praying for the forgiveneſs of ſins (which was not long before he died) were theſe: <hi>But Lord, in ſpecial, I beſeech thee forgive me my ſins of omiſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the general, he had his wiſh and deſire, which he was heard often to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat; and it was, that he might die like Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> who expired as he was cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God for mercy and forgiveneſs. So he went out of this world with much peace, heavenly joy, and ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
               <p>He was ever imployed in his Maſters buſineſs, either in preaching, or reading, or ſtudying, or writing, or elſe (of late, when his eye-ſight failed him) in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others read to him. He was always, either reſolving of doubts, or exhorting, or inſtructing, or giving godly counſel; and yet with this humble expreſſion
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41807:68"/> 
                  <hi>(Lord, forgive me my omiſsions)</hi> did this holy man of God expire, in the 75 year of his age, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1657.</p>
               <p>He was a man of a moſt exemplary moderation, humility, meekneſs, and ingenuity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subpart">
               <head>V. Mr. <hi>Benjamin Rhodes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE had been ſervant to the Counteſs of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and afterward to her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Husband, the Earle of <hi>Elgyn,</hi> as Steward of their houſe.</p>
               <p>God did deal graciouſly with him in his youth: for waiting on the Earle of <hi>Oxford</hi> in the Wars in <hi>Holland,</hi> he was active and valiant, till he was ſuddenly ſtruck at the conſideration, that he might be the author of his brothers death, and that but for a pecuniary ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend; and thereupon he quitted that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and came to wait upon the Counteſs as her Steward.</p>
               <p>Now, the better to know him, he is to be conſidered in a fivefold relation; 1. As a Servant. 2. As a Husband. 3. As
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41807:69"/> a Parent. 4. As a Friend. 5. As a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Son of the Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As a Servant, he ſhewed, 1. His skill, in the imployment he undertook. 2. His fidelity, in not miſpending his time, nor miſimploying the eſtate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge. 3. His diligence, in performing his truſt to his uttermoſt endeavour. 4. His cheerful obedience to all commands, and that in love.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As a Husband, he was loving and tender, both able and apt to teach and inſtruct his Wife; he was free from all kinde of bitterneſs and paſſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As a Parent, his deportment to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his children was diſcreet and grave; he loved them, but not fondly; he was careful in their education, and eſpecially toward the eldeſt, who (only of the two) was yet capable of it, as concerning the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As a Friend and fellow-ſervant, he was juſt and affable; and ſo beloved of all, and bewailed of all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As a Chriſtian, and a dutiful Son
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:41807:69"/> of the Church, wherein he was not only commendable, but admirable, both in life and in death: In the communion of this Church, as he had received his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, ſo he often profeſſed, he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to lay down his life for it. As for the other Sacrament, he would have every man to be highly, and alſo habitually prepared; ſo, as if he ſhould come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Church where it was to be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he ſhould be ready to joyn in it; he and his wife receiving it conſtantly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry month. He was devout and frequent in Prayer; and ſometimes would ſay, <hi>If he ſhould want an opportunity, he would be praying as he ſtood behinde his Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he obſerved, that God by this laſt ſickneſs gave him an effectual call out of this life, his zeal and devotion were doubled, ſo as to inflame the holy affections of all that ſtood about him.</p>
               <p>Having received the Sacrament on the Sunday, a pious ſcruple did ſeize his thoughts, not to ſigne his Will on that day, till by the Miniſter he was ſatisfied.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:41807:70"/>
               <p>He propounded the place of his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial; which ſhewed much of humility, duty and affection. There was at <hi>Malden</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire</hi> a ſtately Monument ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by his Lord, the Earle of <hi>Elgin,</hi> in memory of his deceaſed Lady: <hi>At the entrance into this place,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>himſelf and his wife (if ſhe dyed,</hi> preſaging her ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be alſo mortal) <hi>might conveniently be laid together, that ſuch as ſhould come to view that Monument, might tread upon her ſervants:</hi> yet adding, <hi>That if it were not convenient, he was not ſcrupulous, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted to be interred in the open Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; and that</hi> (to croſs the received ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition) <hi>on the North-ſide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was in ſome trouble, that he had his accounts in no more readineſs for ſuch a ſurprize, till his noble Lord ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him, by no means to diſorder his thoughts about any buſineſs of his.</p>
               <p>Though he was alwayes confident of mercy, yet was he ever humble alſo, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging himſelf the chief of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and declaring ſtill, that this his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41807:70"/> boldneſs ſprang not from his own works, but from Chriſts merits.</p>
               <p>When the Miniſter was to pray with him, he deſired him, <hi>not to intreat fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continuance in this life, his heart was in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finding himſelf almoſt ſpent with ſpeaking, he deſired to have matter of devotion to be adminiſtred to him: thereupon the Miniſter ſuggeſted to him divers ſeaſonable expreſſions; as, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt; Lord Jeſu, receive my ſpirit;</hi> which with great alacrity he repeated after him.</p>
               <p>So great was his patience, as to deſire God to lay his hand more heavy upon him.</p>
               <p>He was nothing ſtartled in his aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the fruition of Chriſt, but cryed out every moment, almoſt, <hi>I go to my Chriſt, I go to my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He thought he ſhould have died on Sunday (though 'twas Munday) and pleaſed himſelf, that he ſhould go from a temporal to an eternal Sabbath.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:41807:71"/>
               <p>When his voice failed him, ſtill his hands held up, ſhewed that his heart was aloft, and that his God ſuſtained him; and ſo he breathed out his pious ſoul into the hands of his bleſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
               <p>He ſickned <hi>July</hi> 24. 1657. and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the 3 of <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subpart">
               <head>VI. Mrs. <hi>Anne Rhodes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SHe alſo was chief ſervant to the Counteſs of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and to her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, the Earle of <hi>Elgin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She was deſcended of the <hi>Glovers,</hi> even of that pious <hi>Glover</hi> in Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> days; who ennobled his lineage, not only in receiving the blood of others, but by ſpending his own, for the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the truth.</p>
               <p>She did diligently attend upon her husband in the time of his ſickneſs, ſo long as her ſtrength continued; but at the laſt, ſhe was forced to yield to the violence of her own ſore diſtemper;
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41807:71"/> where ſhe ſoon perceived, that except ſome remedy were ſpeedily found out, ſhe could not long continue.</p>
               <p>Growing weak, ſhe ſent ſeveral times for the Earl's Chaplen, and he as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly came, and ſpake, and prayed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes with her; and hath profeſſed to receive no ſmall ſupport and comfort by thoſe holy expreſſions that came from her.</p>
               <p>Her husband was high in his aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of enjoying of Chriſt; but it was not ſo with her; ſhe was ſadly torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and brought down almoſt to the gates of hell, with the ſence and terror of her ſins; ſo much, that thoſe preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cordials adminiſtred to her out of the Goſpel, were ſometimes ſcarce able to keep her from fainting.</p>
               <p>But the Chaplen, who was much with her, doth affirm, that he had good ground and great reaſon to judge, that the Lord did hearken to the voice of her weeping; for her deep humiliation, her earneſt invocation, her ſtrong crying for
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:41807:72"/> mercy, her humble requeſt, that her ſins might be made known more fully to her; her juſtifying of God in all his dealings with her; her full reſolution, if God ſhall recover her, to walk more ſtrictly; her holy reſignation to the will of the Lord, to do what he pleaſed with her: Theſe are (he ſaid) infallible evidences, that God, though he chaſtiſed her, and that very ſore, yet he gave her not over to death, the ſecond death.</p>
               <p>As ſhe drew nearer to the time of her departure, ſo did ſhe grow better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the ſlights of Satan, and deluſions of her own heart: ſo ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to a religious Gentlewoman in the Family; <hi>O the craft and ſubtilty of the devil, to make us believe, that this ſin is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and that ſin is nothing; but now</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I finde it to be ſomething!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She was not only contented to live here, or to be gone from hence, as God ſhould pleaſe; but ready alſo to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all other occurrences of divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, with a ſubmiſſive heart.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:41807:72"/>
               <p>There was care had, and ſome ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs uſed, about the acquainting her with her husbands death; ſhe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending them, did quickly make the queſtion, <hi>Is my Husband dead?</hi> Said the Chaplen, <hi>I hope if he be, you are willing to ſubmit to the will of God. Yes,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>with all my heart:</hi> and added, That <hi>ſhould ſhe hear of the death of her two Sons (that then were ſent for) ſhe could willingly ſubmit to Gods good pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When a Gentlewoman, a friend, did ſpirt ſome vinegar out of her mouth, to clear the air in the Chamber, <hi>Spit ſome upon me</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>for I deſerve to be ſpit upon. I, but</hi> (ſaid the Chaplen) <hi>think upon him, that for our ſakes was ſpit upon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like expreſſions of hers, did argue in her, both an humble and a contrite heart, which the Lord will not deſpiſe; and alſo, a quiet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to Gods correcting hand, and then a holy reſignation, and a ready ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of ſuch puniſhment as God
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41807:73"/> ſhould think meet to lay upon her.</p>
               <p>Further, to ſhew that God was graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to her (notwithſtanding the terrors that had been upon her) when the Chaplen wiſhed her <hi>to lift up her heart to God,</hi> ſhe preſently replied, <hi>I do, and the Lord hears me;</hi> which came certainly from the comfortable teſtimony of the holy Spirit, which from a ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, was now become to her a ſpirit of adoption.</p>
               <p>The holy frame of her heart, and the bent of her ſoul, with a ſence of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things, may be judged by ſome let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to her Son, which are in print; and by the tranſlation of the Pſalms, and other eſſays of divine Poetry.</p>
               <p>After ſome ſharp conflicts with death, ſhe did patiently and devoutly yield up her ſpirit into the hands of her gracious Lord, Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>She ſickned the 28 of <hi>July,</hi> and dyed the 4 of <hi>August;</hi> and they were both of them buried in the ſame grave.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subpart">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:41807:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VII. Dr.</hi> Harris his Life and Death.</head>
               <p>HE was born at broad <hi>Campden</hi> in <hi>Glouceſter ſhire,</hi> about the year 1578. and lived till 1658. even fourſcore years.</p>
               <p>After he had been his time at the Free-ſchools in the Country, being by his Parents deſigned, either for Divinity or the Law, he was ſent to <hi>Oxford;</hi> where following his ſtudies, he took the degree of Batchelor of Arts.</p>
               <p>Preparing himſelf for the Pulpit, not the Bar, he offered his firſt pains at <hi>Chipping Campden;</hi> where (though a great Town) a Bible could ſcarce be found, no, not at the Vicars houſe, without much ſearch, being not ſeen ſome months before.</p>
               <p>Upon a fearful plague at <hi>Oxford,</hi> the Univerſity was diſſolved, and few Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars left behinde: he durſt not go home, leſt he ſhould not (by his Father) be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to return thither again, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:41807:74"/> elſe to go he knew not, till by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence he was invited to Mr. <hi>Doily</hi>'s houſe, five miles from <hi>Oxford,</hi> a Family of great piety.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Prior,</hi> the Incumbent there, was aſſiſting to Mr. <hi>Harris</hi> in his ſtudies; which he requited in aſſiſting Mr. <hi>Prior</hi> (a godly man, but ſickly) in his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him.</p>
               <p>By the removal of Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> he was ſetled at <hi>Hanwel,</hi> not far off, where the people were very conformable; ſcarce a family, wherein Gods Name was not in ſome meaſure called upon; nor any that refuſed to be prepared by him for the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edge</hi>-hill-fight was about four miles from him upon the Lords day; he took it for a great mercy, that he heard not the leaſt noiſe of it, till the publick work of the day was over; nor could he believe the report, till a ſouldier (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeared with blood and powder) did witneſs it.</p>
               <p>There happened to be quartered a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:41807:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> company of ſouldiers, that were ſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over to blaſpheming and ſwearing, that he could not forbear uſing that Text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.12. which in the handling did ſo nettle ſome of them, that they damned themſelves to Hell if they did not ſhoot him, in caſe he preached any more upon that Text: but he went on the next day, when in his eye a ſouldier took his Carbine, and fumbled about the lock, as intending ſome miſchief; but the Preacher conceiving it was only to diſturb him, went on with his work, without any farther news of the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</p>
               <p>After this, by a <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Commander, with the treachery of ſome neighbours, he was inforced to ſhift for himſelf, and went to <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From <hi>London,</hi> he (with four other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines) was by the Parliament com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>Oxford,</hi> then under ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and the Chancellor of <hi>Oxford,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Pembrook,</hi> coming to viſit the Univerſity, he was made Dr. of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41807:75"/> which he had refuſed, had it not been the favour of his betters, as being not made thereby the better Scholar, or the better Preacher.</p>
               <p>In continuance of time, when he had ſetled his affairs, and placed his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he left himſelf almoſt nothing more to do, but to prepare himſelf and his wife (50 years married) for their graves; but now the Lord was pleaſed to exerciſe him a new.</p>
               <p>His wiſe, that was religiouſly bred, frequent in holy duties, that ſeldom roſe from her knees with dry eyes, was yet delivered up to Satans buffetting, to ſuch horrors of minde, to ſuch helliſh tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, as grieved every ſpectator. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occaſion, he often ſaid, <hi>The recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of grace, the keeping of grace, the uſe of grace, is all from the Almighty God.</hi> She complaining much and often, that ſhe could finde no comfort; <hi>Oh,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>what an Idol do ſome people make of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, as if their comfort were their Chriſt!</hi> But this cheering he had, that ſhe was
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:41807:75"/> kept, 1. From blaſpheming the higheſt, (ſo ſhe ſtiled God.) 2. From hurting any, in word or deed. 3. That this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction did waken him, ſhe being moſt conſcientious and innocent. 4. It wrought in him a holy deſpair of all creature-comforts; for now he injoyed neither wife, nor childe, nor friend, nor ſleep, as formerly, only inſtant prayers are continued for her upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which gives hopes, that the Lord may pleaſe to make the end comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the conqueſt glorious. So he ſometimes ſaid, <hi>The difference is not great, whether comfort do come in death, or a while after death, ſeeing comfort will aſſuredly come to all that wait with faith and patience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After a long and laborious life, he comes now to a long and a painful ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. In the Summer he began to droop; and when two friendly and learned Phyſicians (Dr. <hi>Bathurſt</hi> and Dr. <hi>Willis</hi>) were ſent for, he profeſſed, <hi>That he uſed means meerly in obedience; that he could be content to live, and durſt die.</hi> He ſaid, <hi>His
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41807:76"/> Phyſicians would loſe of their known worth, having to deal with complicated diſeaſes, which were ſeldom removed; and with old age, which was never cured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His firſt encounter, was with a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Pleuretical pain in his left ſide; to that was joyned a Feaver, and alſo a great defluxion of Rheum, and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Lungs with flegme; and ſometimes not without ſome fits of his old diſeaſe, the Stone and Strangury, which for ſome weeks wrought ſo upon him, as he was not able to ſpeak much to thoſe that viſited him.</p>
               <p>At his firſt ſickening, being deſired to admit of ſome good company, he ſaid, <hi>I am alone in company; it is all one to me, to be left alone, or to have friends about me: my work is now to arm my ſelf for death; and I do apply my ſelf, as I am able, for that great encounter:</hi> And ſo he ſpent his whole time, in Meditation, Prayer and read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, eſpecially the Pſalms, and St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, where he took exceeding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the 10, 14, 15, 16, 17 Chapters.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:41807:76"/> And growing weaker, got others to read to him.</p>
               <p>Still would he be exhorting his viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and attendants to get faith above all; <hi>It is your victory</hi> (would he ſay) <hi>your life, your peace, your crown, and the chiefest piece of your ſpiritual armour: however, get on all, go forth in the Lords might, and ſtand to the fight, and then ſhall the iſſue be glorius, only be ſure not to forget to call in the help of your General; do all by him, and for his glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the Lord's day, he would not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any from publick duty, to do any thing about him; and when the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were ended, he would ſay, <hi>Come, what have ye now for me?</hi> meaning, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition; to which he attended ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, as to ſum up all the heads, and then ſay, <hi>O what excellent truths are theſe! lay them up charily, ye will have need of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being asked where his comfort lay, he ſaid, <hi>In Chriſt, and in the free-grace of God:</hi> and then added, <hi>Work, work apace;
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41807:77"/> dear friends, aſſure your ſelves, nothing will more trouble you, when ye come to die, then that ye have done no more for God, who hath done ſo much for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being again asked, what they ſhould do for him, he ſaid, <hi>Do not only pray for me, but praiſe God alſo for his unſpeakable mercy to me; eſpecially, that in this my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he hath kept Satan from me, and that I ſee the worth of a Chriſt, and do taſte of the ſweetneſs of Gods love more then ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>O how good is God! entertain good thoughts of him.</hi> So he concluded all pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for him, with a loud <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon Saturday-evening, he began to ſet himſelf to die; forbad all Cordials, gave his dying-bleſſing to his Son that was preſent; and calling for the 8th to the <hi>Romans,</hi> he entertained no more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcourſe with the ſons of men.</p>
               <p>Herein God was exceeding good to him, as a return of prayer: his breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were eaſie and even, and his ſoul without the leaſt motion or reſiſtance of the body, did enter into reſt, while we
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:41807:77"/> below were entring upon the day of reſt; for then did he begin a perpetual Sabbath in Heaven, when we begin ours on earth, that is, before one a clock on Sunday morning, 12 of <hi>Decem.</hi> 1658.</p>
               <p>In all the Wills that he made, this Legacy was ever renewed; <hi>Item, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath to all my children, and my childrens children, to each of them a Bible, with this Inſcription,</hi> None but Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Scots</hi> Life and Death.</head>
               <p>SHe was Daughter and Heir to Sir <hi>Matthew Howland,</hi> alſo Heir to her Uncle, Sir <hi>John Howland.</hi> She was firſt married to the Son and Heir of Sir <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Roberts</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> when ſhe was not 17 years old, and afterwards to Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> a worthy Juſtice of Peace in the ſame County.</p>
               <p>She had Sir <hi>Howland Roberts,</hi> and two other Sons, with two Daughters: ſhe was one of a choice ſpirit, of a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſweet temper and diſpoſition, of an
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:41807:78"/> amiable and a winning carriage, and of a religious and charitable converſation.</p>
               <p>About 19 years of age, as ſhe was riding on Hunting, ſhe had a fall from her horſe, and put her leg out of joynt; which was the happy occaſion of her converſion: after this time ſhe never hunted, ſcarce ever came on horſe-back; and ſhe writ it down in a book, among other experiences of Gods goodneſs, eſpecially to her ſoul, reſolving for the time to come, to walk conſtantly in Gods ways; which ſhe made good.</p>
               <p>Once going to the Sacrament, ſhe had grievous temptations, as if ſhe might live without Ordinances, and as if there were no neceſſity of them; but her faith fought againſt it, and ſhe found ſweet comfort and ſtrength in the Sacrament; ſhe received Chriſt, and gave her ſelf up to him.</p>
               <p>She writ in the foreſaid book, the comforts ſhe found in frequent Faſts and Sacraments; concluding with ſuch words as theſe: <hi>My God doth give me
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:41807:78"/> ſweet experiences of the growth of grace in my ſoul, and all from the vertue of Chriſt's blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>This day I was at a Faſt, and God came graciouſly in, and melted my heart, and made good his promiſe to me: They that wait on the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, ſhe writ thus; <hi>This day I did receive Jeſus Chriſt in the Sacrament, and ſo came home rejoycing, and fully aſſured, that all my ſins are pardoned; and that Chriſt may as well be pulled out of Heaven, as I be pulled from Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, out of the ſame book: <hi>I kept a Faſt by my ſelf, to ſeek help from God, in a great ſtraight that I was in; for no power but his could help me out, and deliver me; the Lord did in great mercy aſsiſt me. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, I kept a Faſt in private with others, about the ſame thing: my heart at firſt was out of frame, very heavy and perplexed; but God at length came in, and melted it, and made the duty very ſweet to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, ſhe thought the Ordinances could not be too often enjoyed; and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:41807:79"/> when in Winter-time ſhe could not uſe the Coach to her Country-Church, ſhe would uſually walk on foot, in all the rainy and tempeſtuous weather, that long and tedious, up-hill and down-hill way.</p>
               <p>In <hi>London,</hi> ſhe would be often, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the clock in the morning, at the Lecture at <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> from <hi>High-Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born,</hi> and there ſtay till the ſecond Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was ended.</p>
               <p>She had the grace, as well as the gift of Praying; which was both to admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Every day, ſhe had conſtantly in the Family (morning and evening) Prayer, with ſomething alſo of the Word, and part of a Pſalm ſung: on the Lords day, morning-duties; after dinner, ſinging and praying; and at evening, repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſinging and praying. She was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, a true ſanctifier, and a ſpiritual obſerver of the Lords day, even to a thought, and would often bewail the liberty which too many Profeſſors did
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:41807:79"/> take on thoſe dayes, to talk of civil, and ſometimes of worldly things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any remorſe.</p>
               <p>She never went abroad, but ſhe firſt withdrew her ſelf into her Cloſet, for ſome time to prayer; and the like when ſhe returned home.</p>
               <p>Such exceeding in-comes ſhe had, at the Table of the Lord, the Lord ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that Ordinance to her, that ſhe would often ſay, <hi>She could there fetch from the Lord, any mercy that ſhe wanted;</hi> as, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in ſtraights, ſupport in troubles, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer againſt ſin, conqueſt over ſelf, and grace to carry her on in the wayes of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt her Father, Sir <hi>Matthew How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and her Uncle, Sir <hi>John Howland</hi> lived, ſhe would often ſay, (foreſeeing the ſame, as being their only Heir) <hi>She was afraid of too much of the world to come upon her, and to be an incumbrance to her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As her life, ſo her death, was full of grace and comfort: The Lord did gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſtrengthen her upon her bed of languiſhing; though ſhe was walking
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:41807:80"/> thorow the valley of death, ſhe feared no evil; her God was with her, the Lord ſuſtained her.</p>
               <p>Though her pains and tortures were very great, there being applied to her Cupping-glaſſes with lancings; yet did the Lord put gladneſs in her heart, ſo as ſhe would ſay, <hi>God hath been very good to me; Oh, how good is God! there hath not the leaſt cloud interpoſed between God and my ſoul all this ſickneſs, ſo as I ſhall go to my gracious God triumphing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She would often ſay, <hi>O friends, how ſweet and precious is Jeſus Christ!</hi> And again, <hi>O friends, get an intereſt in Chriſt, and try your faith.</hi> To the ſervants and keepers (that helped to turn her in her bed; for in a few dayes, from Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to Munday, ſhe was by much pain become helpleſs) ſhe ſaid, <hi>I am very weak, but my God is very strong; and there is my comfort, he will lift me up. Oh, praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her eldeſt Daughter ſaying, <hi>Mother, I am going to Church, and to the Sacrament;
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:41807:80"/> That is well,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>but I cannot go: Childe, be ſure to go in the strength of Chriſt, and do all your duties in his strength; and the Lord go with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She would often ſay, That <hi>ſhe did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put on her beſt attire, but ſhe had thoughts of cloathing her ſelf with the rich robe of Christs righteouſneſs, and decking her ſelf with the jewels of his heavenly graces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When her Steward came to ask her any domeſtick queſtion, ſhe would ſay, <hi>Oh, do not trouble me with theſe things on the Sabbath day.</hi> Such was her happy miſtake, ſhe thought all the time of her ſickneſs was a Sabbath; and indeed ſo it was, the Law of the Sabbath was written upon her heart; every day was more and more a Sabbath with her, as ſhe drew neerer her end, as ſhe drew neerer to that reſt which remains for ever; into which ſhe expired, and in which ſhe now triumpheth, with him whom her ſoul loved, and with the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, and with the Angels of God, to all eternity, <hi>Dec.</hi> 1658. <hi>Thanks be to God for his mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:41807:81"/>
               <p>The Preacher at her Funeral, from <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.29. ſpeaking of her unparalleld goodneſs, did number up 10 ſeveral ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies that did ſhine in her; 1. Was her <hi>knowledge,</hi> as being eminently verſt in the methods of grace, and in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of godlineſs. 2. Was her <hi>wiſdom,</hi> by which ſhe brought down all her hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly principles into practice. 3. Was her <hi>humility:</hi> her knowledge did not puff her up; her head was not ſo high, but her heart lay as low. 4. Was her <hi>meekneſs;</hi> ſhe would not provoke any, nor eaſily be provoked by any; ſhe was moſt fearful to give offence, moſt free to forgive it. 5. Was her <hi>mercy;</hi> the love of Chriſt to her, had melted her all into compaſſion, compaſſion to the bodies of poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and compaſſion to the ſouls of all. 6. Was her conſcientious attending on the <hi>Ordinances,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Sacraments, Faſts, Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. 7. Was her <hi>ſtability</hi> in <hi>judgement,</hi> being a well-bottomed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. 8. She was not a <hi>cenſorious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian.</hi> 9. She was of a <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>cheerful
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:41807:81"/> ſpirit,</hi> among croſſes and tryals. 10. She was very good in her <hi>relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> never Mother had a better childe, never child had a better Mother; never ſervants had a better governour, never friends a better friend; ſhe did fill all her relations with wiſdom and fidelity.</p>
               <p>So with gladneſs and rejoycing, was ſhe carried to enter into the Kings Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, into the joy of her Lord, where there is fulneſs of that joy, and pleaſures for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX. Monſieur du Moulins</hi> Life and Death.</head>
               <p>HE was Miniſter of Gods Word, and Profeſſor of Divinity at <hi>Sedan</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> and being 90 years old, died there, <hi>March</hi> 10. 1658.</p>
               <p>During his whole life, he was much given to devotion; but about 3 years and an half ſince, he had a fall from a horſe, after which he had no health, and yet performed his charge conſtantly in the Church, and in the Schools, or elſe privately in Meditation, or in Prayer.</p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:41807:82"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 26. 1658. he awaked in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very ill, but being helped into the Pulpit, he from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.9. preached as it were, his own Funeral Sermon; and giving an account to his Hearers of his faith and hope, he took his leave of them, as if he knew that to be the laſt time (as it was) that he ſhould preach to them.</p>
               <p n="28">28. It being alſo a Sermon-day, he deſired his Colleagues to remember him in the Prayers of the Church. After the Sermon, much company came to him, to bid him farewel, and to receive his bleſſing; ſome had encouragement from him, and ſome had admonition.</p>
               <p>Taking his leave of his Colleagues (for he was thought to be near his end) he ſaid, <hi>Fare ye well, my Masters; I do not doubt, but ye will carefully look to the conduct of the Flock that is committed to you.</hi> One of them ſaid; <hi>The Lord grant, that we may imitate you; you have done good ſervice, and your labours will live when you are gone.</hi> He replied, <hi>Ah, Sir, you know not how
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:41807:82"/> much you grieve me, by ſaying ſo; I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to my ſelf, that I have neglected my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in many things, that I have many wayes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended my God; yet I muſt ſay, that I have loved his holy truth, and do hope in his mercy: he is my Father and my God, and Jeſus Chriſt is my Saviour; whoſoever believes on him ſhall not periſh.</hi> Then he added: <hi>Thou haſt led me, and taught me from my youth: O Lord, forſake me not in the laſt period of my life; have mercy upon me, O God; O my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, have mercy upon me; O Lord, hear me, help me, and ſave me, O my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſaid, <hi>I have been grieved for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of the Church; O Lord, purge and purifie her from all kinde of ſcandal; let her be bleſſed, and let not the adverſaries of the truth triumph over her for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Once coming out of a ſtrong and ſore fit (being a burning Feaver) he ſaid, <hi>O my God, how weary, how tyred am I! When ſhall I reſt in thy boſome, in thy everlaſting arms? when ſhall I be filled with thy hid treaſures? when ſhall I drink of the rivers of thy pleaſures? I am unworthy of it, I
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:41807:83"/> confeſs, O Lord; but thou art glorified by doing good to the unworthy. It is not for them that are whole, but for them that are ſick, that thy beloved Son</hi> (the great Phyſician of ſouls) <hi>was ſent into the world;</hi> whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever believe in him, are paſſed from death to life.</p>
               <p>Being asked by one of the many friends that were about him, Whether he did not perfectly hope in the grace of God that was preſented to him, he ſaid, <hi>I do hope, not perfectly, yet as much as I am able.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt four dayes of his ſickneſs, he was both day and night (with little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion) either in good diſcourſe or in praying; but the ſix laſt dayes, he was much in a deep ſlumber, though he did ſtrive earneſtly againſt it; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times would ſay, <hi>Stir me, prick me, for I ſhould now watch; it is not a time now to ſleep, but to die. O great God, abandon me not to my infirmities, but ſo preſerve and keep up my ſpirit, that I may glorifie thee, even when I am dying.</hi> For a whole day
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:41807:83"/> he was ever and anon ſaying, <hi>The Word was made fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being well awake, a friend asked if he did lift up his heart to God; <hi>O yes,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I do it inceſſantly, and God is gracious to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes he (feeling of his pulſe) would ſay, <hi>O what a grief is this, I cannot die: O good God, have mercy upon me; ſet my ſoul free, ſhorten the dayes of my combat, if it be thy bleſſed will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The two laſt dayes did add to his burning Feaver, and to his deadly ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, contracting of the ſinews, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions; every hour was thought to be his laſt; but about midnight he opened his eyes, ſaying, <hi>I ſhall ſoon be eaſed; I am going to my Father, and to my God; he hath heard me indeed.</hi> And a while after: <hi>I go to him with confidence; for he hath arrayed me with his robe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being raiſed to a rapture not to be expreſſed, he ſaid; <hi>I ſee him:</hi> and (with an acclamation of joy) <hi>Oh, how beautiful he is!</hi> And then (putting ſome by with his
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:41807:84"/> hand) <hi>I renounce all worldly, all earthly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; I will no more love any thing but thee, O God, who dost alone poſſeſs me.</hi> In this rapture, his eyes were clear and ſparkling, his mouth open and panting after the living God, his arms were ſtretched out toward Heaven, and his body ſtriving wonderfully to riſe, as it were, to meet and embrace that beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful object of his love; ſo as all his friends did wiſh and pray, that God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him in that happy inſtant; but his time was not yet come.</p>
               <p>The next day, toward evening, the aſſiſtants perceiving certain ſignes of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching death, did double their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to comfort and ſtrengthen him: he underſtood every thing that was ſaid to him, and ſhewed moſt holy elevati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his prayers, and in theſe words did give them thanks that prayed with him; <hi>The Lord hear you, the Lord bleſs you, for all your labour of love to my poor ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he did hear the glory at hand extolled in ſome emphatical ſentences
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:41807:84"/> of Scripture, he returned into his former raptures, and once more pronounced thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. l. <hi>I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs.</hi> And twice or thrice had theſe words; <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus, come.</hi> And as the laſt time, that Text which he loved ſo much, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world,</hi> &amp;c. and then concluded thus: <hi>Lord Jeſu, receive my ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To him that comforted him with theſe words, <hi>Sir, you ſhall ſoon ſee your Redeemer with thoſe eyes of yours,</hi> he ſaid, with an effort, laying his hand over his heart, <hi>I do ſtedfaſtly believe it.</hi> This was the laſt intelligible ſaying that he did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce; yet did he make ſeveral offers, and great indeavours to be underſtood, and was a quarter of an hour, with much fervent affection, ſpeaking, but the flegme that filled his throat and palate, hindred him.</p>
               <p>His friends making their laſt prayer with him, he did perpetually lift up his eyes and his hands towards Heaven,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:41807:85"/> though he was not able to utter a word.</p>
               <p>Some moments after, he did quietly give up the Ghoſt, dying with peace, and joy, and comfort, which was very viſible in his face: And this was half an hour after midnight, even Sunday morning, when he was going to keep an everlaſting Sabbath in the higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. So all did bleſs the Name of the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Mr. <hi>Crook</hi>'s Life and Death.</head>
               <p>HE was born at <hi>Waldingfield</hi> in <hi>Suff.</hi> in the year 1574. ſon to Dr. <hi>Thomas Crook,</hi> ſometimes Preacher at <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and dyed in 1649.</p>
               <p>From Merchant-Taylors School in <hi>London,</hi> he went to <hi>Cambridge;</hi> &amp; being in <hi>Pembrook</hi>-Hall a while, he was admitted Fellow in <hi>Emanuel</hi>-Colledge, and grew to be well skilled in the <hi>Greek, Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Arabick</hi> tongues, as alſo in <hi>Italian, French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He gave ſeveral Books to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity-Library,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:41807:85"/> as alſo to the Libraries of <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brook</hi>-Hall, and <hi>Emanuel</hi>-Colledge.</p>
               <p>He did uſually preach three times a week: and though by his profound judgement and faithful memory, he could dexterouſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch that with little labour, which coſt others much; yet, he often profeſſed, with rejoycing, that he never durſt ſerve God with that which coſt him but little.</p>
               <p>He did practiſe what he preached; and his <hi>Motto</hi> was, <hi>Impendam, &amp; Expendam; I will ſpend, and be ſpent, for the glory of God;</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly he never gave over ſtudying and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, till all his ſtrength of body failed him: And expecting death, he oftentimes did Preach, as it were, his own Funeral-Sermon.</p>
               <p>It was his care to diſcover to his People, the divine authority, the purity, and the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Scriptures, the Decalogue, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith, the Lord's Prayer, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, God in Trinity, his Decrees, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Providence, the Fall, Sin, Chriſt, the New-Covenant, the Mediator, Goſpel-faith, Vocation, Regeneration, Juſtification, Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, Sanctification, and Glorification; the Church, the laſt Judgement, the Chriſtian warfare, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When his Preaching-day, <hi>Jan.</hi> 17. happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being his birth-day; he alwayes noted his
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:41807:86"/> years, with this penitential cloſe; <hi>God be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to me, a ſinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His divine ſpirit of Prayer ſeemed to excel all other his excellencies; therein he was full of penitent, unbowelling confeſſions, of earneſt deprecations, petitions, pantings and ſighings after God and his grace; of mighty Arguments, by which he uſed to ſet all home; of feeling, thankſgivings, and divine raptures, carrying up his ſoul to Heaven.</p>
               <p>If any Chriſtians came to him for reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in caſes of conſcience, for counſel in ſtraits, for comfort in ſpiritual deſertions, for healing of a wounded ſpirit, he wiſely and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately adminiſtred to their ſeveral occaſions; ſo as they went from him, both ſatisfied and comforted.</p>
               <p>He was never weary of his Lords work; his behaviour was pious: he was grave without auſterity, pleaſant without levity, courteous without diſſembling; he did love uſeful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, but abhorred froth and babling; he was a great Maſter of his own paſſions and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, a great admirer of learning and piety in others, though far beneath himſelf; he converſed more with heaven then with earth.</p>
               <p>Sickneſs at laſt ſeized upon him, and it was full of biting pains, which he bare with much patience; his only grief was, that God had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:41807:86"/> him off from his labour, which was his life and his joy: if he were weary in work, yet was he never weary of work; his ſpirit was ſtill willing, though the fleſh was weak. And now, when he ſaw no more ability for labour, he did account it ſuperfluous to live; &amp; ſo did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cheerfully yield, but patiently deſire to die.</p>
               <p>After that he had in himſelf received the ſentence of approaching death, he deſired his friends not to pray for life, but for faith, for patience, for repentance, and for joy in the holy Ghoſt. His godly friends continuing with him, and bleſſing God for him, he would often ſay, <hi>Alas, I am nothing but a voice,</hi> as being troubled at the increaſing decayes of nature, whereby he was diſabled to do any more work for his Lord and Maſter.</p>
               <p>Some of his laſt words were theſe; <hi>Lord, caſt me down as low as Hell in repentance; but then by a lively faith, raiſe me up to the higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, in an humble holy confidence of thy ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This day ſeven night</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>will be the day on which we have remembred Chriſts nativity, I ſhall ſcarce live to ſee it; but, for me alſo was that Childe born, unto me alſo was that Son given, who is Wonderful, Counſellor, the mighty God, the everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is now come to the end of his labours, and to the beginning of his reſt; his work was
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:41807:87"/> with God, &amp; his reward ſhall be from his God. And thus did ſet this bright occidental Star, upon the day of the Lords Nativity, being the 75 year of his age. He had been a Preacher 47 years, even to above 7000 Sermons.</p>
               <p>As he was full of dayes, ſo was he full of grace, and full of peace, and full of aſſurance; yea, he was full of the trueſt honour, for his worth and works ſake, in the hearts of all that feared God. His memory ſhall be bleſſed, and his name ſhall be a ſweet perfume to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</p>
               <p>So let us leave this happy Brother of ours in the bed of Honour, until the joyful morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the bleſſed Reſurrection of the juſt.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>This was finiſhed about the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> which was the day of my Nativity, and now the ſeventieth year of my age, and of our Redemption, 1664.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:87"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:88"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41807:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
